<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter concerning the Council of Trent</title>
            <author>Jenks, Sylvester, 1656?-1714.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 158 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46798</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J630C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217051</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828752</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828752</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33183</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46798)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33183)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1968:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter concerning the Council of Trent</title>
                  <author>Jenks, Sylvester, 1656?-1714.</author>
                  <author>N. N.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>147-264 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: Sept. 22. 1686.</note>
                  <note>Possibly a fragment of a larger work; caption title begins on G2.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Council of Trent (1545-1563) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="147" facs="tcp:33183:1"/>
            <head>A LETTER Concerning the <hi>COVNCIL</hi> OF TRENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>R,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Having peruſed the
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>The Hiſtory of the Council of</hi> Trent, <hi>written in Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian by</hi> Pietro Soave Polano, <hi>tranſlated by</hi> N.B. <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> London. 1676. <hi>in</hi> fol. <hi>pages</hi> 769. <hi>If my Reader have a different Edition, he may obſerve his whole num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of pages, and (by the Rule of Three) as this of mine is to that, ſo will my quotations be to his.</hi>
               </note> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor you ſo much recommended to me, I am apt to fancy that never any two Hiſtorians diſagreed more than yours &amp; mine; the one ſo zealous in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alting,
<pb facs="tcp:33183:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:33183:2"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:33183:3"/>the other in depreſſing of the Council. But yet I am not of opinion that this was the only difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wixt them. <hi>Pallavicini</hi> had the freedom of the <hi>Vatican</hi> Archives; He referrs himſelf to the Records of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, &amp; the writings of
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>He ſetts down their names,</hi> l, 8. c. 10. n. 14.</note> ſuch Perſons as were Members of it: Moreover, He is ſo far from being partial, that
<note n="*" place="bottom">D. Still. <hi>Rat. Account.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Aquilino</hi> ſays He has done the Church more diſſervice by his <hi>Anſwer,</hi> than his Adverſary had done by his <hi>Hiſtory.</hi> As for your friend <hi>Soave,</hi> I am afraid he's apt to make the worſt of things, even when he ſpeaks truth as to the ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce. His intimate acquaintance with the Archbishop of <hi>Spalatro,</hi> &amp; his correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondency with the <hi>French Huguenots.</hi> are enough to make me ſuſpicious of him. If you tell me, he was a <hi>Popish Frier,</hi> I muſt mind you, that he was a <hi>Venetian Papiſt,</hi> that he lived in a time of great diſſentions betwixt the State of <hi>Venice</hi> and the Pope, &amp; that he was even then engaged in writing againſt the Pope's proceedings. Tis hard to ſay how much he was a friend to the <hi>Church,</hi> But any man may ſee how bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:33183:3"/>an enemy he was to the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> He liked well enough to be medd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with State-Affairs, &amp; the Senators conſulted him as an Oracle: which unuſual honour was enough to make him proud &amp; factious; and, whether it did or not, He only knows who ſees men's hearts. However all this put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether is enough to make me ſuſpect him. <hi>Pallavicini,</hi> you'l ſay, being of the Court-party deſerves to be ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted too. But, if that be all you have to ſay againſt him, we will not quarrel about preliminaries, nor looſe time in diſputing what grains of allowance are due to each of them. Upon condition you'l believe your friend <hi>Soave</hi> when he ſpeaks well of the Council, I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to believe <hi>Pallavicini</hi> whenſoever he ſpeaks ill of it.</p>
            <p>You remember how eaſily, when I ſaw you laſt, you agreed with me, that <hi>if the Council of</hi> Trent <hi>were as General, as free, and as legal in all it's circumſtances, as the firſt four Councils were, you muſt needs own your ſelf obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in conſcience, to ſubmit to it, &amp; to leave of Proteſting againſt it.</hi> 'Twas fair &amp; reaſonable, &amp; what I might expect from a Son of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England:</hi>
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:33183:4"/>I deſired no more in hand, but was willing to give credit for the reſt.</p>
            <p>I might have told you that if the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil had been only Patriarchal; it would have bound the English Reformers to the obedience of non-contradiction. Three Brittish Bishops ſate in the I. Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Arles:</hi> &amp; S. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in his 2. <hi>Apol.</hi> ſays that they were preſent in the Council of <hi>Sardice,</hi> which ratified the Pope's power in deciſion of Appeals: From whence you may conclude, that the <hi>Brittish</hi> Clergy were ſubject to the canons of <hi>Arles</hi> &amp; <hi>Sardice,</hi> &amp; conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Weſtern Patriarch. We find them alſo afterwards in the Council of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> where voting by Nations the English were one of the four in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning theſe doctrines of <hi>Huſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> &amp; <hi>Wickliff,</hi> that <hi>The Pope is not the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Vicar of Chriſt,</hi> &amp; that <hi>The chief Bishop of the Roman Church has no Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy over other particular Churches.</hi> I might have added the teſtimony of your own D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Field,</hi> who in his book <hi>of the Church</hi> freely confeſſes, that <hi>The Decrees of Popes made with the conſent &amp; joynt concurrence of the other Weſtern Bishops, do bind the Weſtern Provinces that are ſubject to him as Patriarch of the Weſt.</hi>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:33183:4"/>But this is not the caſe: the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> is truly General; and, if the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers cannot manifeſtly prove the contrary, they remain without excuſe. The Objections which you ſent me in your Letter, I have conſiderd at leaſure, and according to promiſe, have ſent you here my Anſwers: but, before I ſet them down, I muſt beg your pardon if I try your patience with ſome few re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks which follow. <hi>Ch. Gov.</hi> P. IV.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A General Council requires, either the preſence of all the Catholick Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs, or their Legates, with the Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops of ſo many Provinces as can well convene, or their Delegates; or elſe (in their neceſſary abſence) it requires that the Acts &amp; Decrees be approved, either by all, or by the major part of the abſent Prelates.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As for ſuch a General Council as comprehends all the Bishops of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Univerſe, there never was yet any. We find always a greater or leſſer number, according to divers cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances; propinquity of place, peace of Princes, numeroſity of Sects, &amp;c. The firſt four Councils, of <hi>Nice, Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Epheſus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> by reaſon of the Oriental Hereſies, were held in the
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:33183:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Eaſt, &amp; conſiſted principally of Oriental Bishops. In the I. were preſent only the Pope's two Legates, &amp; three Weſtern Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops. The II. had no Weſtern Bishop at all, but only was afterward confirm'd by the Pope &amp; his Council. The III. had only three Delegates, ſent by the Pope &amp; his Occidental Council. They tranſacted moſt of their buſineſs, &amp; condemn'd <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> without the preſence of the <hi>Antiochian</hi> Patriarch. The IV. had only four Legates ſent by the Bishop of <hi>Rome,</hi> two <hi>African</hi> Bishops, &amp; one <hi>Sici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian.</hi> They acted without <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> the <hi>Alexandrian</hi> Patriarch, They depoſed him for favouring Hereticks, &amp; for his contumacy againſt the See of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. If all <hi>Catholick</hi> Prelates, or the much greater part, by perſonally preſent in the Council, there's no need of far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther acceptation to confirm it. But, this wanting, 'tis ſupplied by the after-ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation of ſuch perſons as are capable of a vote, and ſo many as, if they had been preſent, would have made it the much greater part of <hi>Catholick</hi> Prelates, that is, of ſuch as were not before shut of the Church by Hereſie or Schiſme. The II. &amp; V. General Councils became ſuch by the confirmation &amp; after-accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:33183:5"/>of <hi>Damaſus</hi> &amp; <hi>Vigilius</hi> with their Weſtern Bishops: and 'tis a funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental principle of Government not ſimply Monarchicall, that No Laws can be promulgated, no Unity pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, if of their Governours the leſſer part be not regulated by the greater.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Council remains General, notwithſtanding the abſence of ſome conſiderable Churches: 1. if they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conveniently come: 2. if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe without juſt hindrance: 3. if they were formerly cut of by Hereſie or Schiſme. The Catholick Church is narrower than Chriſtianity and a Council may be General, though the Church were reduced to one Patriar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chate.</p>
            <p n="5">5. All that were capable of a voice in any General Council, were ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon'd to <hi>Trent.</hi> The Eaſtern Bishops, in the <hi>Turks</hi> Dominions could not conveniently come, there being war betwixt <hi>Chriſtians</hi> &amp; <hi>Turks.</hi> The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, which occaſion'd the Aſſembly, aroſe only in the Weſt, &amp; therefore there was leſs need of their preſence. Moreover ſix <hi>Greek</hi> Bishops ſate in the Council: And, ten years after, the <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenberg</hi>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:33183:6"/>Divines ſent the <hi>Auguſtan</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion to <hi>Hieremy</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> whoſe Anſwer to them differs very little from the Decrees of <hi>Trent.</hi> Tis true; <hi>Cyril Lucar</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">1629.</note> publish'd a Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viniſtical Confeſſion: But his immediate Succeſſor <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Iberia</hi> aſſembled at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> a Synod of 23. Bishops, beſides the Patriarchs of <hi>Alexandria</hi> &amp; <hi>Hieruſalem;</hi> And again, his Succeſſor <hi>Parthenius</hi> aſſembled another of 25. Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops, &amp; amongſt them the Metropolitan of <hi>Moſcovy:</hi> Both theſe Synods anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiz'd <hi>Lucar</hi> with his Adherents; and alſo juſtified theſe Tenets of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, the <hi>Corporal Preſence of Chriſt's Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy &amp; Blood with the Symboles; Invocation of Saints; Veneration of ſacred Images; Prayer &amp; Almes for the Faithfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceas'd with repentance, as betterable in their preſent condition by them; Free will; ſeven Sacraments; Church Infallibility,</hi> &amp;c. See <hi>Leo Allatius, De perpetuo Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſu</hi> &amp;c. l. 3. See Monſieur <hi>Arnauld</hi>'s Answer to <hi>Claude</hi> l. 4 ch 7.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The abſence of the Proteſtant Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy from the Council did not hinder it's being General. 1. They who are not Bishops, have no right to ſit there. 2.
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:33183:6"/>When Bishops contumaciouſly abſent themſelves for fear of Cenſure, their preſence is not requiſite; otherwiſe fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well the Power of all General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils. 3. There is no place due to them whoſe Doctrines have been anathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd in former General Councils. <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Images</hi> was declared lawfull in the II. of <hi>Nice.</hi> Our <hi>Canon</hi> of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Purgatory; Seven Sacraments,</hi> &amp; <hi>Pope's Supremacy,</hi> were defined in the Council of <hi>Florence:</hi> Auricular <hi>Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> &amp; <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> in that of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Although in the firſt Seſſions under <hi>Paul</hi> III. there were only about 48. Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops, 3. Benedictine Abbots, 5. Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals of Religious Orders, with about 40. able Divines by way of Counſellors: This paucity under <hi>Paul</hi> or <hi>Julius</hi> was amply recompenc'd by a greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Prelates under <hi>Pius</hi> IV who all unanimouſly received &amp; ratified the former Acts of the Council. If you count them, you'l find in the Catalogue, 270. to which if you add the learned Divines who aſſiſted, the whole number a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts to about 450. perſons.</p>
            <p n="8">8. A General Council requires, that the Pope either preſide in it; or approve
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:33183:7"/>the Acts of it, as in the caſe of the II. &amp; V. General Council. In the IV. VI. VII. &amp; VIII. the Proteſtants allow that he preſided. To the III. he depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted S. <hi>Cyril.</hi> To the I. he ſent his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates. <hi>Oſius,</hi> you'l ſay, ſubſcrib'd before them. 1. Tis thought he preſided in the Pope's name with them 2. If not, it was a pure indulgence of honour to him: The Legates ſubſcribed before all the Patriarchs. 3. The ſubſcriptions were manifeſtly irregular, becauſe the Bishop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> who was the III. Patriarch, ſuſcribed after the Bishops of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> &amp; alſo thoſe of <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> which were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to him. I have now done with my remarks, &amp; shall make what haſt I can with your objections, ſetting them down in the ſame order you ſent them.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The Eaſtern Bishops were abſent: &amp; the Proteſtants would not go to the Council. A. 1. There were ſix <hi>Greek</hi> Bishops preſent: Afterwards three Eaſtern Patriarchs, &amp; two Aſſemblies of their Prelates approv'd the chief points. The Proteſtants had no right to a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſive voice: Their opinions had been cenſur'd in former Councils, and were like to be condemn'd again in this: If, for theſe reaſons, they abſented; 'twas
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:33183:7"/>their own fault: The Council was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the worſe for't. 2. Read the Bulls of Convocation: you will find that <hi>all</hi> &amp; <hi>every one</hi> who, either by <hi>law,</hi> by <hi>cuſtom,</hi> or by <hi>priviledge,</hi> have any right to <hi>be preſent,</hi> or to <hi>deliver their opinion,</hi> in <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councils,</hi> were ſummon'd to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in <hi>Trent.</hi> 3. <hi>Soave</hi> himſelf relates how there was a deliberation of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, &amp; granting ſafe-conduct, to the <hi>Greek</hi> Churches under the <hi>Turk;
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 451.</note> but it was preſently ſeen,</hi> ſays he, <hi>that theſe poor men afflicted in ſervitude, could not without danger, &amp; aſſiſtance of money, think of Councils.</hi> He ſays alſo, that
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 408.</note> 
               <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Pope was put in mind, that to ſend Nuncio's into</hi> England <hi>&amp; to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces elſewhere, who do profeſs open Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from the See of</hi> Rome, <hi>would be a diſreputation to him; yet he answer'd that he would humble himſelf to Hereſy, in regard that whatſoever was done to gain ſouls to</hi> Chriſt, <hi>did become that See.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. In ſome of the firſt Seſſions there were not above fifty Bishops. A. The difficulties &amp; diſturbances of the Times bear all that blame. All was fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenc'd in the end, by a numerous
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:33183:8"/>&amp; unanimous ratification of all, &amp; by the acceptation of the abſent Prelates after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. <hi>Soave</hi> ſays, that, under <hi>Pius</hi> IV.
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 504.</note> 
               <hi>the Actions of this Council were in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter expectation than in former times, in regard the number of the Prelates were aſſembled four times as many as before.</hi> He ſays,
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 757.</note> 
               <hi>All the Decrees made in this Council, under</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Julius, <hi>as well of Faith as Reformation, were recited: And the Secretary going into the midſt did interrogate, whether the Fathers were pleas'd that Confirmation should be demanded of Pope</hi> Pius IV. <hi>of all things decreed under</hi> Paul, Julius, <hi>&amp; his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and they anſwer'd, not one by one, but all together,</hi> Placet. <hi>Pallavicini</hi> ſays the ſame; only he proves that
<note n="*" place="bottom">l. 24. c. 8.</note> the votes were given, as uſually, one by one.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Many of the Bishops were only Titular: And many made, during the Council, that the <hi>Papalins</hi> might over-vote the <hi>Ultramontans.</hi> A. As to the firſt part; <hi>Soave</hi> takes notice only of two Titular Bishops, the Archbishop of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magh</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Upſal</hi> in <hi>Sweden;</hi> both driven from their Sees by perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Proteſtants, both true Bishops by their Ordination, and both ſent by the
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:33183:8"/>Pope in the beginning of the Council. The ſecond part, being barely aſſerted, looks like a groundleſs calumny, &amp; may juſtly be ſuppos'd ſuch, till ſome proof appear.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. The Popes, of thoſe times, &amp; major part of the Prelates, would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver allow this Title, of the Council, <hi>Repreſenting the Univerſal Church:</hi> Therefore they themſelves did not look upon it as a General Council. A. Here I muſt beg your pardon, if I think you very much miſtaken in your inference. This Title was uſurp'd by the Councils of <hi>Conſtance</hi> &amp; <hi>Baſil;</hi> but never aſſum'd by any Council, which was totally approv'd. You know very well, that Catholick Divines are divided upon the point; whether the Pope be ſuperior to a General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil; or whether a General Council, without him, be ſo compleat a Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative of the Univerſal Church, as to be ſuperior to the Pope? They who maintain'd the ſuperiority of a General Council, were zealous for this Title; and the others conſtantly oppos'd it: But both parties always agreed, that the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent</hi> was as truly <hi>General,</hi> as the firſt four Councils were, or any have been ſince.</p>
            <pb n="160" facs="tcp:33183:9"/>
            <p n="5">V. It was never receiv'd by the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants:</hi> Nor by the <hi>French</hi> Catholicks. A. 1. The Council of <hi>Nice</hi> was never receiv'd by the <hi>Arians.</hi> 2. It was uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally receiv'd by both <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> &amp; <hi>Civil</hi> State of <hi>France,</hi> in point of <hi>Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine</hi> 3. The Decrees of <hi>Reformation</hi> were approv'd by all the <hi>Catholick Clergy</hi> of that Kingdom. In the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly at <hi>Blois,</hi> in the year, 1576. The Archbishop of <hi>Lions</hi> in the name of all the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical State</hi> of <hi>France</hi> begg'd the <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> of the <hi>King's Authority</hi> to <hi>put this Reformation in execution.</hi> In the Aſſembly of <hi>Melun,</hi> 1579. the <hi>Bishop</hi> of <hi>Bazas,</hi> in their name, made the ſame requeſt to the King, <hi>chiefly becauſe they are tied &amp; bound to all Laws, ſo made by the Catholick Church, upon pain of being reputed Schiſmatical, &amp; of incurring the curſe of Eternal Damnation.</hi> At <hi>Fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainebleau,</hi> in the year, 1582. The Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of <hi>Bourges</hi> tells the King, <hi>The ſtain &amp; reproach of Schiſm reſts upon your Kingdom amongſt other Countries. And this is the cauſe, why the Clergy doth now again moſt humbly deſire,</hi> &amp;c. In the General Aſſembly of the States at <hi>Paris,</hi> in the year, 1614. Cardinal <hi>Perron,</hi> &amp; Cardinal <hi>Richelieu,</hi> then Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hop
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:33183:9"/>of <hi>Luſon,</hi> proſecuted in vain the ſame requeſt. Thus you ſee the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Clergy</hi> of <hi>France</hi> unanimouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving &amp; approving the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> in matter of <hi>Diſcipline.</hi> The <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil State,</hi> as it has no share in the Votes of the Council, ſo their non-appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation cannot diminish the Authority of it. You may gueſs at the reaſons of excepting againſt it, by what the Queen Regent, <hi>Catherine de Medicis,</hi> was pleas'd to tell the Pope's <hi>Nuncio;</hi> that <hi>the Council could not be admitted, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by the Council's Decrees the King could not gratifie ſuch Miniſters of State, as had done him ſingular ſervice, with the means of Religious Houſes, &amp; of Church-Benefices.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">VI. <hi>Leo</hi> X. before the Convocation of the Council, had declar'd that <hi>Luther</hi> &amp; his <hi>Adherents</hi> were Hereticks: Being therefore already condemn'd, why should they come to Council? A. 1. Their Errors had been condemn'd in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer General Councils: and, ſince it real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was ſo, Why might not the Pope ſay ſo? 2. <hi>Becauſe</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> had condemn'd them <hi>therefore</hi> they
<note n="*" place="bottom">See <hi>Soave</hi> p. 11.</note> appeal'd to a <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Council:</hi> and, ſince they had <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal'd</hi>
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:33183:10"/>to it, Why should they not <hi>go</hi> to it?</p>
            <p n="7">VII. It was not a legal Council. A. That is to ſay, it was not ſuch a one as they had a mind to. <hi>Luther,</hi> being que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion'd, firſt made friends to be tried in <hi>Germany.</hi> As ſoon as he was there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd by <hi>Cajetan,</hi> he appeal'd to the Pope. Immediately after, foreſeeing his condemnation there, he intercepted this appeal with
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>ibid.</hi> p. 8.</note> another, from the Pope to a General Council; having ground to imagine, He would never call one, who was ſuppos'd, to fear that it would ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely reform him &amp; his Court. As ſoon as he ſaw that, in good earneſt, a Bull was publisht, in the year, 1537. to call a Council at <hi>Vicenza;</hi> he began preſently, to vilifie Councils, &amp; put out a book <hi>De Conciliis,</hi> to prove that they always did more harm than good; not ſparing ſo much as the firſt Councils of <hi>Nice,</hi> or of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Then he appeal'd from Council to <hi>Scripture,</hi> where He that makes himſelf ſupreme Judge of the Senſe, may eaſily maintain what ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity he pleaſes. <hi>Soave</hi> tells us, he was
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 17.</note> 
               <hi>uſed to ſay that he was ſo well aſſured of his Doctrine, that, it being
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:33183:10"/>Divine, he would not ſubmit it ſo much as to the judgment of Angels; yea, that with it he was to judge all, both men &amp; Angels.</hi> After this, his Followers thought it more plauſible not to shuffle ſo viſibly, but to admit a Council, &amp; clog it with ſuch conditions as would quite diſarm it, &amp; make it uſeleſs. You may read them in <hi>Soave,</hi> as follows.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">p. 600.</note> 1. <hi>That it should be celebrated in</hi> Germany; 2. <hi>That it should not be inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated by the Pope;</hi> 3. <hi>That He should not preſide, but be part of the Council, ſubject to the determinations of it;</hi> 4. <hi>That the Bishops &amp; other Prelates should be freed from their Oath given to the Pope;</hi> 5. <hi>That the Holy Scripture might be Judge in Council, &amp; all Humane Authority excluded;</hi> 6. <hi>That the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines of the States of the</hi> Auguſtan Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, <hi>ſent to the Council, might not only have a conſulting, but a deciding voice;</hi> 7. <hi>That the Deciſions in Council should not be made, as in Secular mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, by plurality of voices; but the more ſound opinions preferr'd, that is, thoſe which were regulated by the word of God.</hi> You will not deny, but that in <hi>England</hi> we have had ſome Kings
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:33183:11"/>whoſe title to the Crown has been unqueſtionable, &amp; that ſome free &amp; legal Parliaments have been aſſembled during their reign. Give me leave to put the caſe, that two or three Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties had revolted, proteſting againſt all that would be done in ſuch a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; refuſing to ſend any Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to it, but upon theſe conditions: 1. that it be aſſembled in their Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritory; 2. that it be not call'd by the King; 3. that his Majeſty may be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to it; 4. that all the members of it be freed from their Oath of Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance; 5. that all Humane Authority of former Parliaments may be exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; 6. that they may depute as many as they pleaſe with a deciſive voice; 7. that (for fear of being over-voted) the Deciſions be not made, as uſually, by plurality of voices, but that the more ſound opinions, (that is, their own) may be preferr'd. What would you think of theſe Articles? Would you conclude, the Parliament was illegal, if it did not ſubmit to their demands? I do not pretend here, to make an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act parallel betwixt the <hi>Monarchy</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> &amp; that of <hi>England:</hi> yet however the parity is not ſo unequal,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:33183:11"/>but that it may help to open your eyes.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. The Parties concern'd were Judges in their own caſe. A. No more than in the I. of <hi>Nice.</hi> The world was then divided into Catholicks &amp; <hi>Arians,</hi> as now into Catholicks &amp; <hi>Proteſtants:</hi> And, as the <hi>Catholicks</hi> had then a right to judge the one, ſo now they had the very ſame right to judge the other. If any part ſeparate from the whole, it does not therefore acquire a right of ſaying, that the Whole, from which they divide themſelves, is now a Party, &amp; therefore muſt not judge them. Pope <hi>Leo</hi> and <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> Bishop of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria</hi> counteraccus'd one another of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy; and yet the Pope legally preſided in the IV. General Council which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd <hi>Dioſcorus,</hi> Neither was it ever thought a ſufficient excuſe for <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> to ſay, the Pope was a Party &amp; Judge in his own caſe.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Chilling worth</hi> confeſſes, that, in controverſies of Religion, <hi>it is in a manner impoſſible to avoid but the Judge muſt be a Party. For this muſt be the firſt controverſy, whether he be a Judge or no; and in that he muſt be a Party.</hi> Such is the Pope's Caſe, in the Definition of his Supremacy. The ſame
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:33183:12"/>neceſſity is found in ſupreme <hi>Civil</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer. Inferiour Courts are liable to Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals: But, if ſome of the King's ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects rebell againſt him, &amp; oppoſe his prerogatives or laws; 'tis evidently ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that the King muſt judge his own caſe, or the Offence muſt not be judg'd at all. What muſt the King do? Subſtitute an equal number of Royaliſts &amp; Rebells? This can never be an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual proviſion for the Common Peace of Government. Or muſt he remit the arbitration to a neighbouring State? 1. This ſtate is always intereſs'd; &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore partial. 2. This does not leave, within the compaſs of any Kingdom upon earth, ſufficient power to procure the common good. 3. Were it allow'd in <hi>Civil</hi> Power, it cannot be applied to our preſent caſe, unleſs Controverſies in Religion could be decided out of the Church, by men of no Religion at all.</p>
            <p>In the National Synod of <hi>Dort,</hi> in the year, 1618. the Low-country <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrants</hi> ſeeing themſelves like to be over-voted by the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> made the ſame excuſes; ſaying, that the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part of the Synod was declar'd of a contrary party; that they were already
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:33183:12"/>excommunicated by them; and, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, they ought not to be Judges. To this, the Synod replied: that, if this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception were admitted, it would ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the whole frame of Eccleſiaſtical Government: that Paſtors would be diſcourag'd from their duty of oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the firſt beginnings of Hereſy, if therefore they muſt forfeit their right of giving ſuffrages, or being Judges, afterwards: that the <hi>Arians</hi> &amp; <hi>other Hereticks</hi> might ever have pleaded the ſame exception againſt the Orthodox Fathers: that Divines neither are, nor ought to be, indifferent in matters of Religion; ſo that, if only Neuters may be judges, there will be none left in the Church, and we muſt go abroad (no body knows where) to look for 'em. This was the ſubſtance of their Anſwer; which I here ſet down in the Latin, to ſatisfie your curioſity. <hi>Nunquam praxim hanc Eccleſiarum fuiſſe, ut Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtores, quoties exorientibus erroribus ex officio ſe opponerent, propterea jure ſuffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giorum, aut de illis ipſis erroribus judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candipoteſtate, exciderent, Ita enim om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem everti judiciorum Eccleſiaſticorum ordinem; efficique ne Paſtores officio ſuo fideliter fungi queant .... Eos qui in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinâ
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:33183:13"/>aut moribus ſcandalorum autores ſunt, ſemper Cenſores ſuoge, Conſiſtoria, Claſſes, Synodos, ceu partem adverſam, rejicere .... ad eum modum Arianis, aliiſque olim hereticis, adverſus Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxos Paſtores ſemper licuiſſet excipere.</hi> The <hi>English</hi> Divines deliver'd their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in theſe terms: 1. <hi>Huic ſententiae re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragatur perpetua praxis omnium Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiarum. Nam in Synodis Oecumenicis, Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caeno, &amp;c. ii. qui antiquitus receptam doctrinam oppugnarunt, ab illis, qui ean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſibi traditam admiſerunt &amp; appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barunt, examinati, judicati, damnati ſunt.</hi> 2. <hi>Ipſius rei neceſſitas huc cogit. Theologi enim, in negotio religionis, neque eſſe ſolent tanquam abraſae tabulae, neque eſſe debent. Si igitur ſoli neutrales poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent eſſe judices, extra Eccleſiam in quâ lites enatae ſunt, quaerendi eſſent.</hi> 3. <hi>Ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa aequitas ſuadere videtur. Nam quae ratio reddi poteſt, ut ſuffragiorum jure priventur omnes illi Paſtores, qui ex of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficio receptam Eccleſia Doctrinam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnantes ſecus docentibus adverſati ſunt. Si hoc obtinuerit, nova dogmata ſpargentibus nemo obſiſteret, ne ipſo fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to jus omne poſtmodum de illis controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiis judicandi amitteret.</hi> Pray, give me leave now to ask, Why might not the
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:33183:13"/>Parties be Judges in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> as well as in the Synod of <hi>Dort?</hi> If, in one caſe, the <hi>Remonſtrants</hi> were oblig'd to ſubmit to the <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> Why were not the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> oblig'd to ſubmit to the <hi>Catholicks</hi> in the other? The Synod was forc'd to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſome diſparity; and, for want of a better, alledg'd this; that the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> and <hi>Remonſtrants</hi> were under the <hi>ſame Magiſtracy.</hi> And, what if if they were? We are not now talking of <hi>Civil</hi> Aſſemblies, but of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical.</hi> Dos the diviſion of <hi>Civil</hi> Power de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the <hi>Unity</hi> of the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> which we believe in our <hi>Creed?</hi> Or, if there be any reaſon why (when any Schiſme ariſes) the <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> of the <hi>Whole</hi> is devolved to the <hi>major part,</hi> does not the ſame Reaſon conclude as evidently in favour of a <hi>General,</hi> as of a <hi>National,</hi> Council?</p>
            <p n="9">IX. To make it better appear, which was the <hi>major part,</hi> the Proteſtants ought to have had a deciſive voice in Council. A. 1. <hi>Binius</hi> ſays, that the Council premitted this caution; that, if the Proteſtants were allow'd, for once, to give a <hi>Placet,</hi> it should be no prejudice to the right &amp; honour of
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:33183:14"/>the preſent &amp; future Councils: which looks as if the Council were not fully reſolv'd to deny this to them, if much inſiſted upon. 2. They, who openly maintain ſuch doctrines as have been formerly condemn'd in General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, are cutt of from the Catholick Church; they are not Members of it; &amp; therefore can have no right to a deciſive voice. 3. If it had been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, they were ſtill certain to be over-voted by 270. Bishops; to whom if you add the Catholick Divines, by the ſame rule as the Proteſtants, there remain'd no ground for any hopes. This the Proteſtants ſaw well enough, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were willing to wave all <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical</hi> Judges. <hi>Soave</hi> tells you, how they shuffled in this point. One time, they propoſed a Deciſion by <hi>Laicks</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently choſen, in an equal number, on both ſides. Another time, they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal'd to
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 73.</note> 
               <hi>a godly &amp; free Council,</hi> which <hi>is not the Tribunal of Pope &amp; Prieſts only, but of all the Orders of the Church, not excluding the Seculars.</hi> Here indeed the <hi>Clergy</hi> were admitted to this <hi>godly &amp; free Council;</hi> but it was only, by way of ſpectators, to ſee what
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:33183:14"/>the <hi>Laity</hi> would pleaſe to do there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for
<note n="*" place="bottom">ibid.</note> 
               <hi>the Pope making himſelf a party to the cauſe, it</hi> was <hi>juſt that the manner and form of the proceeding, should be determin'd by the Princes.</hi> This was the
<note n="*" place="bottom">ib.</note> 
               <hi>Anſwer of</hi> 15. <hi>Princes, &amp;</hi> 30, <hi>Cities, aſſembled in</hi> Smalcalda, 1535. Again, about two years after, when the
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 76.</note> 
               <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour ſent his Vice. Chancellor to exhort them to receive the Council,</hi> they anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werd, that <hi>they</hi> had <hi>always demanded a free &amp; Chriſtian Council, that every man may freely ſpeak, Turks &amp; Infidels being excluded.</hi> Here you ſee, that every man, who call'd himſelf a Chriſtian, (no matter how otherwiſe qualified) was to have a free Vote in Council: only Turks &amp; Infidels were to be excluded. Judge you, what a <hi>free</hi> &amp; <hi>godly</hi> Council this was like to be. Mean time, all this was only a copy of their countenance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> They clearly foreſaw that the much greater part, of thoſe to whom God has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the care of his Church, would certainly condemn their errors: They were already ſelf-condemn'd, as to Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; And therefore they never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to appear in any legal Council, but hated the very thought of it: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:33183:15"/>the Name of a Council was very plauſible, and fit to be made uſe of, for a time, to amuſe the world with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> an opinion of the Reformers, that they were not proud &amp; obſtinate; but always willing to hear reaſon, &amp; deſirous to be better informed.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Pruſſia</hi> was more ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, when <hi>Canobius</hi> came to invite him; He
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 413.</note> 
               <hi>anſwer'd</hi> plainly, without any mincing or diſguiſing of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>that he was of the</hi> Auguſtan <hi>Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, &amp;</hi> therefore <hi>could not conſent to a Popish Council.</hi> Yet, after all, to do the Proteſtants juſtice, I muſt needs confeſs that, as ſoon as they were no longer in fear of the Emperour, they began to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mask &amp; ſpeak as plainly as the Duke did. Read <hi>Soave</hi>'s Annals, 1562. he ſays that,
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 599.</note> 
               <hi>ſo ſoon as the Diet was aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in</hi> Francfort, <hi>the Prince of</hi> Condé <hi>ſent to treat an union of the</hi> Huguenots <hi>with thoſe of the Confeſſion of</hi> Ausburg; <hi>and, in particular, to make a joynt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, for a free &amp; new Council, in which the reſolutions of</hi> Trent <hi>might be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd, the</hi> French <hi>men of the old Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Religion giving hope alſo that they would agree unto it ... But the</hi>
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:33183:15"/>Dutch <hi>Proteſtants were moſt averſe from a Council, ſo long as</hi> Germany <hi>might be in peace without it. And therefore a book was printed in</hi> Francfort, <hi>full of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why they neither would, nor could, come to</hi> Trent, <hi>with proteſtation of the nullity of all that was, or would be, done in that place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One thing, which makes me leſs wonder they could never agree to any Council of ours, is this, that I find in <hi>Soave,</hi> they could not agree in a Council of their own.
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 411.</note> In <hi>Germany,</hi> ſays he, <hi>the Princes of the</hi> Auguſtan <hi>Confeſſion, aſſembled in</hi> Neumburg, <hi>being ashamed that their Religion should be eſteem'd a Confuſion for the variety of Doctrines amongſt them, did propoſe that they might firſt agree in one, &amp; then reſolve whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ought to refuſe or accept the Synod ... They ſaid, the</hi> Auguſtan <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion was to be the ground of their Dot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine; but, there being divers copies of that Confeſſion, which differ'd, in regard of divers additions made in divers of them, ſome approving one &amp; ſome ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Many thought they ought to take that only which was preſented to</hi> Charles <hi>in the year,</hi> 1530. <hi>Whereunto thoſe
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:33183:16"/>of the</hi> Palatinate <hi>did not conſent, unleſs it were declared, in a Proheme made unto it, that the other Edition did agree with it. The Duke of</hi> Saxony <hi>anſwer'd, that they could not ſtop the eyes &amp; ears of the world, that they should not ſee &amp; hear their differences; &amp; that if they would make shew of union, where they were at variance, they should be convinc'd of vanity &amp; lying: And, after many contentions, they remain'd without agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in that point.</hi> How should the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks pleaſe them, if they knew not how to pleaſe themſelves?</p>
            <p n="10">X. The burning of <hi>John Huſs</hi> was a ſufficient excuſe for the Proteſtants, not to rely upon any Safe conduct, A. I muſt beg your pardon, if I believe no ſuch matter. It was no excuſe at all. His Safe conduct was of the <hi>ordinary</hi> form; Theirs was <hi>extraordinary:</hi> And, there fore the Caſe was quite different.</p>
            <p>'Tis certain that the <hi>Ordinary</hi> Safe-conducts ſecure a man only from <hi>unjuſt violence,</hi> but not from the <hi>juſt execution of a legal ſentence,</hi> if he be found guilty. When a perſon, ſuſpected of a crime, is cited to appear, &amp; to anſwer for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, the <hi>Ordinary</hi> Safe-conduct ſecures him from all abuſes or affronts which
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:33183:16"/>might otherwiſe be offer'd to him, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther going, ſtaying, or returning: but however, if, after a fair Trial, he be legally condemn'd: it will never ſave him from ſuffering according to Law. If this were all the Security that <hi>Huſs</hi> relied upon, we may juſtly admire his confidence, in going ſo boldly to the Council; but can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reaſonably wonder, either at his impriſonment, or execution.</p>
            <p>That this was all the Security given him, appears by the teſtimony of one of his own Diſciples, who wrote his <hi>Acts</hi> which are publish'd in the beginning of his Works, &amp; ſays he was an eyewitneſs of what paſs'd. He relates the words of the Emperour <hi>Sigiſmond</hi> telling <hi>Huſs</hi> to his face, at <hi>Conſtance;
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Acta Iohannis Huſs.</hi> p. 15.</note> Although,</hi> ſays he, <hi>Some ſay that, by your friends &amp; patrons, you receiv'd our Letters of Publick Faith, fifteen days after your impriſonment; yet we can prove, by the teſtimony of many Princes &amp; men of chief note, that, before you leſt</hi> Prague, <hi>you receiv'd our Letters by</hi> Wenceſlaus <hi>of</hi> Duha. <hi>&amp;</hi> John <hi>of</hi> Chlum, <hi>to whoſe truſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty care we recommended you, THAT NO INJURY MIGHT BE DONE TO YOU, but that you might ſpeak freely,
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:33183:17"/>&amp; anſwer for your ſelf, before the whole Council, concerning your faith &amp; doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. And this, you ſee, the moſt Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Lords, Cardinals &amp; Bishops, have ſo perform'd, that I have reaſon to give them many thanks ... Now therefore we adviſe you, not to defend any thing ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately, but to ſubmit your ſelf, with what obedience you ought, to the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Holy Council. If you do this, we will endeavour, that, for our ſakes, you may be favourably diſmiſs'd by the Council. If not ... We truly will never patronize your obſtinacy &amp; your errors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this diſcourſe of the Emperour I obſerve, 1. That the <hi>Letters of Publick Faith</hi> were given to <hi>Huſs,</hi> only <hi>that no injury might be done to</hi> him: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conclude, that, if contrary to the common law of Safe-conducts he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to make his eſcape, his impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was juſt, and no injury done. See <hi>Bremus</hi> a Proteſtant Lawyer, <hi>Quaeſt. ult. de Securitate,</hi> who cites a great number of others, agreeing with him this opinion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that <hi>Publick Faith is ended or forfeited, if a man, having receiv'd Publick Faith, committs a new crime, be cauſe, for this, he may be punish'd.</hi> 2. That the friends of <hi>Huſs</hi> made no great
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:33183:17"/>ſcruple of telling ſtories in favour of him, &amp; of raiſing a falſe report that the <hi>Letters</hi> were given him the fifteenth day after his confinement; thinking, perhaps, that by this rumour the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour would be oblig'd in honour, to reſcue him out of priſon: Which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful dealing makes me leſs wonder, either that his Diſciples make no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his endeavouring to eſcape, or that the Nobles of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> take no notice of it in their Letters of complaint to the Emperour; &amp; makes me more apt to believe the Relation of it, ſet down by <hi>Ulricus Reichental,</hi> an inhabitant of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> an eye witneſs of what hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, &amp; an accurate Hiſtorian of the Council, whom if you underſtand not in the original <hi>Teutonick,</hi> you may read this part tranſlated into <hi>Latin</hi> by <hi>Coch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laeus,</hi> lib. 11. <hi>Hist. Huſſitarum,</hi> pag. 73.</p>
            <p>Before <hi>Huſs</hi> was guilty of this crime, he had been <hi>kindly receiv'd</hi> and <hi>favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably treated</hi> at <hi>Conſtance,</hi> as well as all the way thither. This he confeſſes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, in his Letters to his friends.
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>We came,</hi> ſays he, <hi>to</hi> Conſtance, <hi>after the feaſt of All Saints, paſſing through the
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:33183:18"/>Cities without any ill uſage, And we lodge in a ſtreet which is nigh the Pope's Palace.</hi> Again;
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Ep.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>All my affairs are in a good poſture,</hi> ſays he; <hi>Scitote quod bene ſto per omnia.</hi> And, in his Letter above cited, ſpeaking of <hi>Latzem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bock</hi> and <hi>Lepka</hi> to whoſe care the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour had recommended him, he ſays,
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Ep.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>They have been with the Pope, &amp; have ſpoken to him concerning me; Who anſwer'd, that he will do nothing by violence.</hi> Beſides, his Chamber-fellow <hi>Plebanus de Jannowitz</hi> wrote a Letter dated from <hi>Conſtance,</hi> the Saturday be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore S. <hi>Martin</hi>'s feaſt; in which he tells, how
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Ep.</hi> 4. <hi>Huſsiticarum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the Bishop of</hi> Conſtance <hi>with his Official, came to their Lodging, let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them know that the Pope ſuſpended the interdict &amp; the ſentences of excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication againſt Maſter</hi> John; <hi>deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him nevertheleſs, that, to avoid ſcandal &amp; diſcourſe of the People, he would abſent himſelf from the ſolemn ſervices of the Maſs; otherwiſe, that he might freely go about to ſee the Town, the Churches, or any other places, as he pleaſed.. We have,</hi> ſays he, <hi>full liberty in</hi> Conſtance.</p>
            <p>Afterwards, as <hi>Ulricus</hi> relates it, <hi>the
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:33183:18"/>people flock'd together, to hear</hi> Huſs <hi>ſay Maſs in his Lodging;</hi> which being a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous thing, (he having been excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated for Hereſy, &amp; not having yet juſtified himſelf) <hi>the Bishop of</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, <hi>as Ordinary of the place, prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited</hi> his doing ſo: But, <hi>Huſs</hi> ſtill perſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>to celebrate, &amp; the Bishop forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the people to be preſent,</hi> he began to look upon it as an evil <hi>omen</hi> of his future condemnation, and reſolv'd to contrive his eſcape. <hi>Upon the third Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day in Lent, when</hi> Huſs <hi>did not appear at dinner,</hi> Latzembock <hi>went immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Governour of the City, and complain'd of the flight of</hi> John Huſs. <hi>The gates being shut,</hi> &amp; ſearch made, <hi>Huſs</hi> was <hi>found hid in a Cart</hi> of the ſame <hi>Latzembock,</hi> where he lay cover'd <hi>with hay &amp; ſtraw,</hi> which had been or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd to be tranſported out of town, that afternoon. <hi>Latzembock</hi> made <hi>him</hi> be <hi>ſet on horſe back, &amp; brought him to the Pope's Palace. He pleaded, that, having Safe-conduct, he ought not to be impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon'd.</hi> But this Noble <hi>Bohemian</hi> (who knew very well what Safe-conduct he had, he being committed to his care, by <hi>Signiſmond</hi>) anſwer'd, <hi>'Tis ſo Decreed, that either you muſt juſtifie your Cauſe,
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:33183:19"/>that it is not heretical; or die, unleſs you renounce it.</hi> I do not ſay, this was not ſevere; The Imperial Laws are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere enough: but yet, ſince it was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Common Law of <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary</hi> Safe-conducts, it cannot be truly call'd an <hi>Injury,</hi> And, by the ſame rule, that the Emperour was not oblig'd, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Letters, <hi>to patronize his obſtinacy &amp; his errors,</hi> neither was he oblig'd to protect him from the courſe of Common Law in this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs I am apt to believe, that the Emperour did really deſign to procure (as much as he could, by fair means) more favour for him than the rigour of the Law allow'd. Among other reaſons which incline me to this opinion, theſe two may ſuffice at preſent: 1. that <hi>John Chlum</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Inter Epiſt. Huſsiticas.</hi> num. 57.</note> complain'd, his Maſter's Safe-conduct was violated: 2. that the Emperour himſelf in his Anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to the Nobles of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> writes, He
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Cochlaus</hi> l. 4, <hi>Hiſt. Huſsitarum.</hi> p. 155.</note> 
               <hi>often ſollicited for him; often, in a paſſion, went out of the Council; yea rather, upon his account, departed from</hi> Conſtance; <hi>till they ſaid,</hi> If You will
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:33183:19"/>not give Juſtice leave to take its courſe in Council, what have We to do here? <hi>Whereupon</hi> ſays he, <hi>I concluded, it was not in my power to do any thing more, in this matter. Neither was it lawfull for me to ſpeak any more, of this Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; becauſe, by ſo doing, the Council would have been diſſolv'd.</hi> Thus He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved himſelf; And, whether it were Vanity, or Generoſity, or Policy, that moved him, is not my buſineſs to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire; Tis enough for your ſatisfaction &amp; mine, that, by his <hi>Letters of Publick Faith,</hi> He was not oblig'd, either in Conſcience, or in Honour, to reſcue him out of the hands of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> but only to protect him from <hi>Unjuſt Violence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tis incredible, you'l ſay, that <hi>Huſs</hi> should be ſuch a fool as to go to <hi>Conſtance</hi> upon theſe terms. Neither can I deny but that it muſt be ſome degree of folly for any man to be ſo confident of his own abilities as to cope with a whole Council, &amp; to defie all his Oppoſers to convince him of his errors. But why might not the Maſter be as bold as the Scholar? I mean <hi>Jerome</hi> of <hi>Prague</hi> who follow'd him ſoon after, to <hi>Conſtance,</hi> upon the ſame terms, with a Safe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct from the Council.
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>Citamus ...
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:33183:20"/>quatenus compareas ... recepturus, ac facturus, in omnibus Juſtitiae comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum, ad quod A VIOLENTIA, JUSTITIA SEMPER SALVA, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Salvum-conductum noſtrum, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum in nobis eſt, &amp; Fides exigit Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxa, praeſentium tenore offerimus.</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve theſe words, <hi>a violentiâ;</hi> The Safe-conduct was only to ſecure him from unjuſt <hi>violence.</hi> Obſerve alſo the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing clauſe, <hi>Juſtitiâ ſemper ſalvâ;</hi> He was not to expect any protection againſt <hi>Juſtice.</hi> If <hi>Jerome</hi> deſired no more than this from the Council, Why might not <hi>Huſs</hi> be content with as much from the Emperour?</p>
            <p>That this was the <hi>Ordinary form</hi> of all Safe conducts, granted according to Common Law, appears evidently by the general conſent of Lawyers; among which, for your better ſatisfaction, I shall cite only ſuch as were Proteſtants. <hi>Bremus,</hi> q. 7. <hi>de Securitate,</hi> ſays, this is the common Imperial form of Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conducts; <hi>Damus tibi Fidem Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam, cauſam dicendi in Judicio, CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TRA VIM, NON CONTRA JURIS EXECUTIONEM. Mynſingerus,</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv. 82, upon the Judgment of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Chamber, ſays, <hi>Quando datur
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:33183:20"/>alicui Securitas, vel Salvus-conductus, Tunc intelligitur ſolum de VIOLEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIA, quae de facto CONTRA JUS in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fertur. Et ideo, meo tempore, cuidam, qui habebat Salvum-conductum, capto propter delictum, vel maleficium, &amp; ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canti in Camerâ pro Mandato de relax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ando ... petiti Proceſſus a Dominis Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſoribus ſunt denegati.</hi> Again, <hi>Everar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Specklan,</hi> another Lawyer, <hi>Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riâ</hi> 1. q. 1, §. 18. cites a great many Authors, All agreeing that ſuch is the uſual form. And, in the <hi>Jus Camera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le,</hi> Tit. 276. (See the Edition of <hi>Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſtus</hi>) this Law of <hi>Maximilianus Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus</hi> is read; <hi>Subditos Judicio Rotwi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſi avocaturi, Fidem actori Publicam. CONTRA VIM, NON CONTRA JUS, dare tenentor.</hi> Any man, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands <hi>Latin,</hi> ſees plainly by theſe quotations that <hi>Common Law,</hi> in ſuch Caſes, always grants <hi>Security</hi> from <hi>Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> but not from <hi>Juſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Huſs</hi> had no Safe-conduct from the <hi>Pope,</hi> he expreſſely acknowledges, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 6. <hi>I came,</hi> ſays he, <hi>to</hi> Conſtance, <hi>without Safe-conduct from the Pope.</hi> That he had none from the <hi>Council,</hi> appears not only by his ſilence, but by <hi>Soave</hi>'s Hiſtory, <hi>pages,</hi> 298. <hi>&amp;</hi> 307.
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:33183:21"/>which I shall cite in the following Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection. That the Safe-conduct, which he had from the <hi>Emperour,</hi> was never intended to hinder the Council's pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding againſt him, according to the Canons, is manifeſt, not only by what has been already ſaid, but by the Emperour's <hi>Letters of Publick Faith,</hi> dated from <hi>Spire,</hi> Octob. 18. 1414. extant in <hi>Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daſtus</hi> his <hi>Appendix Documentorum ad Commentarios de Regni Bohemiae Juri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus &amp; Privilegiis.</hi> p. 81. <hi>We heartily recommend, to all &amp; every one of you, the honourable Maſter</hi> John Huſs <hi>Batch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elor of Divinity, &amp; Maſter of Arts, the Bearer of Theſe, whom We have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into Our protection &amp; Safeguard of the Holy Empire, paſſing from the Kingdom of</hi> Bohemia <hi>to the General Council which is shortly to be held in the City of</hi> Conſtance: <hi>Deſiring you to receive him kindly, &amp; treat him favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably whenſoever he shall come unto you, and that you will &amp; ought to shew your readineſs, in promoting what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to his ſpeed &amp; ſafety, either by Land or Water, permitting alſo, him, his ſervants, his horſes, &amp; all things elſe beionging to him, freely, &amp; without any hindrance, to paſſe, to ſtop, to ſtay, &amp; to
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:33183:21"/>return, by any paſſages, ports, bridges, lands, dominions, juriſdictions, cities, towns, caſtles, villages, &amp; whatſoever places of yours, without any expence of tribute, toll, or any other payment; And, that you will, &amp; ought, for the honour &amp; reſpect of our Majeſty, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide Secure &amp; Safe conduct for him &amp; his, when occaſion shall 'require.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this the Emperour commanded, as much as lay in Him, And, in all this, his ſubjects obeyd, as much as lay in them. He had no Authority over the Council, in matters of Religion: Nor do I find the leaſt ſyllable of any promiſe, made by the Emperour to him, that the Council should not proceed againſt him, according to Law. He came upon his good behaviour, and in his own defence; confiding in his own prudence and abilities, as well as in the Emperour's Letters; in which there is no ſign of theſe two promiſes, 1. that he should not be impriſon'd, if by any miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour he deſerv'd it; 2. that he should nor be executed, if legally condemn'd.</p>
            <p>Both theſe promiſes were plainly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the <hi>Extraordinary</hi> Safe-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct which the <hi>Tridentine</hi> Council granted to the <hi>Proteſtants:</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:33183:22"/>as I told you in the beginning, The Caſe was quite different. Read <hi>Soave,</hi> and if you believe him, you'l begin to be asham'd of your objection.
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 348, <hi>Conc. Trid Seſſ.</hi> 15. &amp; 18.</note> 
               <hi>The Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod doth make Faith to all Prieſts, Princes, &amp; Perſons of what condition ſoever ...Safe conduct, to come, remain, PROPOSE. &amp; ſpeak IN THE SY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOD, to HANDLE &amp; EXAMINE WHAT THEY THINK FIT. give Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, &amp; confirm them, ANSWER the OBJECTIONS of the Council, &amp; DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PUTE with thoſe, whom it doth elect, declaring that the CONTROVERSIES in this Council shall be handled accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the HOLY SCRIPTURE, Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of the APOSTLES, approv'd COUNCILS, Conſent of the CATHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LICK CHURCH, &amp; Authority of the Holy FATHERS; adding, that they SHALL NOT BE PUNISH'D upon PRETENCE OF RELIGION, or OF<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FENCES COMITTED, or which WILL BE COMMITTED ...and shall RETURN, when it shall ſeem good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, WITHOUT LET, with SAFE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TY OF THEIR ROBE, HONOUR, &amp; PERSONS, but with the knowledg of the Deputies of the Synod, that
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:33183:22"/>proviſion may be made for their Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: granting that, in this Safe-co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, ALL thoſe CLAUSES be held to be included, which are NECESSARY FOR REAL &amp; FULL ASSURANCE: Adding, that if any</hi> of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, <hi>either in coming, or in Trent, or in returning, SHALL COMMIT ANY ENORMITY, which shall NUL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIFIE THE BENEFIT OF THIS PUBLICK FAITH, he shall be PU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NISH'D BY THEIR OWN</hi> Proteſtant <hi>JUDGES, ſo that the Synod may be ſatisfied: and, on the other ſide, if any</hi> Catholick <hi>in coming hither, remaining here, or returning, SHALL COMMIT ANY THING which may VIOLATE THIS SAFE CONDUCT, he shall be punish'd by the Synod, WITH AP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PROBATION OF THE GERMAN</hi> Proteſtant<hi>'s THEMSELVES, who shall be preſent in Trent.... which things it promiſeth faithfully, in the name of all faithfull Chriſtians, Eccleſiaſtical &amp; Secular.</hi> If <hi>Huſs</hi> &amp; <hi>Jerome</hi> had come to <hi>Conſtance</hi> with ſuch a Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conduct, they had neither been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon'd, nor executed. With ſuch a one as this, the <hi>Bohemians</hi> went after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to <hi>Baſil,</hi> were civilly uſed, &amp;
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:33183:23"/>return'd quietly home. With this the <hi>Wittenberg</hi> Proteſtants went to <hi>Trent,</hi> remain'd quiet there, &amp; return'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out receiving any affront. That no more of the Proteſtants follow'd their example, in going thither, was their own fault: They knew very well, they might have gone, remain'd, &amp; return'd, ſecurely, if they pleas'd. Confider all this, at leiſure; and then, tell me (if you can) what's become of your Excuſe.</p>
            <p n="11">XI. The Councils of <hi>Conſtance</hi> &amp; <hi>Sienna</hi> had declared it lawfull to break the faith of any Safe-conduct what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. A. Read the Decrees; you'l plainly ſee the contrary. The Council of <hi>Conſtance</hi> dos not ſay, 'tis lawfull for any, whoſoever they are, to violate the faith of their promiſes; but only declares, that no <hi>Secular</hi> Power can legally hinder the exerciſe of <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuſtical</hi> Juriſdiction, becauſe it is, not only independent of it, but manifeſtly ſuperior to it, in matters of Religion. Tis a common Maxim of the Law; <hi>Superior legibus aut pactis Inferioris non ligatur.</hi> And, in all appearance, the deſign of the Council was to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the World, that, although the
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:33183:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>Emperour had pretended to grant an <hi>Extraordinary</hi> Safe-conduct, ſuch as exempts a man from <hi>Juſtice</hi> as well as <hi>Violence,</hi> it could nor have hindred the ſupreme Power of Pope &amp; Council from proceeding according to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, in Cauſes which are purely of Religion.</p>
            <p>This was the reaſon why the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants would not rely upon the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour's Safe-conduct; Nor can I blame them for it. See <hi>Soave,</hi> p. 298. <hi>Duke</hi> Maurice <hi>wrote to the Emperour, that his Safe-conduct was not ſufficient. For, in the Council of</hi> Conſtance, <hi>it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd, that THEY MIGHT PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CEED AGAINST THOSE THAT CAME TO THE COUNCIL, THOUGH THEY HAD SAFE-CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DUCT FROM THE EMPEROUR.</hi> And that, therefore <hi>the</hi> Bohemians <hi>would not go</hi> Baſil, <hi>but under the Publick Faith of the whole Council.</hi> See p. 307. The Ambaſſadors <hi>went all together to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents,</hi> &amp; told them, that <hi>the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour had given</hi> the Proteſtants <hi>a Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conduct, but that they were not conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with it, alledging that it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed in the Council of</hi> Conſtance, <hi>and really executed, that THE COUNCIL
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:33183:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>IS NOT BOUND BY THE SAFE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CONDUCT OF ANY, WHOSOEVER HE BE; &amp; therefore they required one from the Synod.</hi> Theſe Proteſtants, you ſee, underſtood the Council in the ſame ſenſe as I do: How come you to underſtand it otherwiſe?</p>
            <p>Let the <hi>Decree</hi> ſpeak for it ſelf, &amp; judge caſe betwixt us. It runs thus: <hi>Preſens Sancta Synodus, ex QUOVIS SALVO CONDUCTU per Imperato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem Reges, &amp; alios Seculi Principes, HAERETICIS vel de Haereſi diffama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, putantes eoſdem ſic a ſuis errori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus revocare, quocunque vinculo ſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrinxerint,</hi> CONCESSO, NULLUM <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei Catholicae, vel JURISDICTIONI ECCLESIASTICAE, praejudicium gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari, vel IMPEDIMENTUM PRAES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TARI POSSE ſeu DEBERE declarat, QUOMINUS dicto Salvo-conductu non obſtante, LICEAT JUDICI competen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti &amp; ECCLESIASTICO de hujuſmodi perſonarum erroribus IN QUIRERE, &amp; aliàs contra eos DEBITE PROCE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DERE, eoſdemque PUNIRE, QUAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TUM JUSTITIA SUADEBIT, ſi ſuos errores revocare pertinaciter recuſave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint, etiamſi de Salvo conductu confiſi ad locum venerint Judicii, aliàs non
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:33183:24"/>venturi: Nec ſic promittentem, cum fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerit quod in ipſo eſt, ex hoc in aliquo remanſiſſe obligatum.</hi> Conc. Conſt. <hi>Saſſ</hi> 17.</p>
            <p>The Council does not ſay, that any one, who makes a promiſe, is not obliged in conſcience to keep it, to the utmoſt of his juſt &amp; lawfull power: But only declares, that every man's Promiſes, &amp; Obligations of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, are confined within the limits of his own Juriſdiction, which he cannot lawfully exceed; And that, therefore, No man either can promiſe, or be by promiſe oblig'd to perform, any more. This is the plain ſenſe of thoſe words: <hi>Nec ipſum promittentem</hi> Imperatorem, Regem, vel alium quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis Secoli Principem, <hi>cum fecerit quod in ipſo eſt,</hi> quod nimirum, ex officio, &amp; jure ſuo, poteſt ac debet, <hi>ex hoc</hi> Salvo-conductu, <hi>in aliquo,</hi> quod Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictioni obſit Eccleſiaſticae, <hi>remanſiſſe</hi> ulteriùs <hi>obligatum.</hi> Can you blame this Doctrine? Does not every body know, 1. that any man <hi>may</hi> promiſe, &amp; every man <hi>ought</hi> to perform, what lies in his power?  2. that no man can, either promiſe to encroach upon a power ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior to his own, or be oblig'd to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form it?</p>
            <pb n="192" facs="tcp:33183:25"/>
            <p>The 1. <hi>Act</hi> of the Council of <hi>Sienna</hi> proceeds upon the ſame principles. Though it was very inconſiderable in its iſſue &amp; concluſion, it was General in its convocation &amp; deſign; It imitated the Council of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> in aſſuming the Title of <hi>Repreſenting the Univerſal Church;</hi> And, by vertue of the ſupreme Eccleſiaſtical Power implied in that Title. They commanded All Governours Eccleſiaſtical &amp; Secular, to proſecute the Laws againſt the followers of <hi>Huſs</hi> &amp; <hi>Wickliff,</hi> revoking &amp; forbidding all <hi>priviledges, immunities, exemptions, &amp; Safe-conducts</hi> whatſoever; <hi>Privilegiis, Exemptionibus, Immunitatibus, SAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VIS CONDUCTIBUS, a quibuſcumque Perſonis, Eccleſiaſticis vel Secularibus, etiamſi Pontificali, Imperiali, Regali, aut Ducali; aut aliâ quâcumque Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticâ vel Seculari praefulgeant dignita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, conceſſis vel concedendis, NON OB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STANTIBUS QUIBUSCUNQUE.</hi> You may look upon this Perſecuting Decree as a ſevere thing, &amp; blame it (if you pleaſe) upon that account: But you cannot juſtly blame the Doctrine upon which 'tis grounded, it being the very ſame with that of the Council of <hi>Conſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="193" facs="tcp:33183:25"/>
            <p>If you ask me, Why then dos the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> inſert this clauſe in the end of the Safe-conduct, that
<note n="*" place="bottom">p 348.</note> 
               <hi>the Synod shall not uſe, or ſuffer any to uſe, any authority, power, right, ſtatute, or priviledg, of laws, canons, or Councils, ESPECIALLY that of</hi> Conſtance, <hi>&amp; of</hi> Sienna; <hi>which things, in this behalf, &amp; for this time, the Council doth diſallow?</hi> Why dos it <hi>diſallow</hi> theſe Statutes, if they were fair &amp; juſt? A. It dos not diſallow them <hi>abſolutely,</hi> but only <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionally;</hi> that is, <hi>IF</hi> they contain any doctrine contrary to the Security of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith. The reaſon of this procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding was, becauſe among the Proteſtants there were a great many who had an ill opinion of theſe Decrees, and were very jealous of them. 'Twas more eaſy for the Council to proteſt, that, whatſoever they were, they should not prejudice the Safe-conduct; than it was, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them that the Decrees were inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. It was the charitable deſign of the Council to uſe all condeſcenſion poſſible, and give ſuch an <hi>extraordinary</hi> Safe-conduct, as might prevent all jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies &amp; take away all excuſes. And here it is, that the Synod might juſtly
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:33183:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſay, what the Pope ſaid upon an other occaſion, They
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 408.</note> 
               <hi>humbled themſelves to Hereſy, in regard that whatſoever was done to gain ſouls to Chriſt, did become that</hi> Council.</p>
            <p>If you have a mind to ſee a great deal more of this charitable conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſion towards them, read <hi>Soave</hi>'s Hiſtory, where he tells you how, the Council having granted them a Safe conduct in the 13. Seſſion, they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted againſt it, &amp; demanded another of a more ample form, which was ſoon after granted, &amp; publish'd in the 15. Seſſion, <hi>Jan.</hi> 25. 1552. Obſerve how <hi>Soave</hi> relates it.
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 343<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour's Ambaſſadors deſired to have the draught of</hi> it, <hi>before it was publish'd, to shew it the Proteſtants, that if it did not give them ſatisfaction, it might be ſo amended, that they might not have an occaſion to refuſe it, as they did the other.</hi> Afterwards <hi>the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour's Ambaſſadors call'd the Proteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants to them, &amp; the Ambaſſador</hi> Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tavius <hi>exhorted them to give ſome little part of ſatisfaction to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, as they receiv'd much from it; told them that it was concluded, to
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:33183:26"/>receive their Mandates &amp; Perſons, and to hear their Propoſitions, and to defer the concluſion of the points of Doctrine, though already diſcuſs'd &amp; digeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to expect the Divines, and hear them firſt; that they have a very am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Safe-conduct, as they deſired ... that it was neceſſary to yield ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the time, &amp; not to deſire all at once; that when they shall be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the buſineſs, occaſion will make them obtain many things which before ſeem'd hard ... that they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the Emperour's Ambaſſadors, have matters to propoſe of great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and do ſtand only expecting that the Proteſtants should begin, that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards they themſelves may come forth alſo. For this cauſe he prayed them to proceed ſlowly in their demand, that the Pope should ſubmit himſelf to the Council. For the Fathers do know that there is ſomething to be amended in the Papal greatneſs; but withall, that they muſt go on cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly; that they themſelves have dayly experience, what dexterity &amp; art muſt be uſed in treating with the Pope's Miniſters. Therefore let their Divines come, who should have a convenient
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:33183:27"/>audience in all things, and when they shall ſee themſelves wrong'd, it shall ever be free for them to depart. The Proteſtants retiring &amp; conſidering the draught of the Safe-conduct, were not content. They required four things more;</hi> 1. <hi>a deciſive voice;</hi> 2. <hi>that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, &amp; interpreters conformable to it, should be Judges;</hi> 3. <hi>that they might exerciſe their religion in their own hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes;</hi> 4. <hi>that nothing should be done in contempt of their doctrine.
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 349.</note> The Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts perſwaded them to go on with dexterity; ſaying, as before, that with time they should obtain all; but, ſeeking things diſtaſtfull, &amp; before there was opportunity, every thing would be more hard:</hi> that the 3. article <hi>was under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood to be granted, becauſe it was not forbid:</hi> &amp; that the 4. <hi>was plainly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd, becauſe good uſage was promis'd.</hi> Ambaſſador <hi>Toledo</hi> had told them,
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 344.</note> 
               <hi>that the chief importance was in the Security of coming &amp; departing; that the reſidue appertain'd to the manner of their Negotiation, which might more eaſily be concluded by the preſence of the Divines, that it was too much obſtinacy, to yield in nothing, &amp; to deſire to give
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:33183:27"/>laws to the whole Church.</hi> After all this,
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 352.</note> 
               <hi>the Proteſtants receiv'd the Safe-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct; but, with proteſtation, that they did it, only to ſend it to their Princes.</hi> Would not any body think, theſe men were very hard to pleaſe?</p>
            <p n="12">XII. When ſome of the Proteſtants came to <hi>Trent.</hi> they were denied au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, &amp; liberty of diſputing. A. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the one, nor the other, was denied them. Tis true, they were not heard: but whoſe fault was that? It was becauſe the victorious Army of the Proteſtants made the Bishops run away from <hi>Trent,</hi> before the preliminaries of the Treaty could be well agreed upon. They came about the middle of <hi>March,</hi> &amp; departed in the beginning of <hi>April.</hi> Have but a little patience to hear <hi>Soave</hi> tell the ſtory, and you will preſently ſee that this objection is a meer calumny.
<note n="*" place="bottom">ibid.</note> 
               <hi>The Electors of</hi> Mentz <hi>and</hi> Collen <hi>departed the eleventh of</hi> March.... <hi>four Divines of</hi> Wittenberg <hi>and two of</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentina <hi>came to</hi> Trent <hi>afterwards,</hi> &amp; deſired <hi>to begin the Conference. The Legat anſwer'd, that the nineteenth of</hi> March <hi>being a day appointed for the Seſſion,</hi> they would then conſider about
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:33183:28"/>
               <hi>a form how to treat.</hi> Was this, denying audience? Afterwards a <hi>reſolution</hi> was <hi>taken, to prolong the Seſſion till the firſt of</hi> May. This was ſome Delay indeed, &amp; little enough to deliberate upon the preliminaries of ſo unuſual a Treaty; but however, it was no Denial. Mean time,
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 352.</note> 
               <hi>the Proteſtants often deſir'd the Action should begin</hi> (it ſeems, they were in great haſt) but <hi>difficulty was ſtill rais'd, ſometimes about the manner of treating, ſometimes about the matter with which to begin...
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 353.</note> the Adherents of</hi> Ceſar, <hi>Spaniards, &amp; others, mov'd by the Emperour's Ambaſſadors, deſired to proceed; but the Papalins</hi> (he has always a fling at the Court) <hi>ſuſpecting that the end of the Imperialiſts was to come to the Reformation of the Court of</hi> Rome, <hi>embrac'd all occaſions of delay. The Legate,</hi> ſays he, <hi>was thought to feign</hi> himſelf ſick; but <hi>Soave,</hi> I preſume, did not think ſo himſelf, becauſe he tells us in the very next page, that <hi>he died</hi> ſoon after at <hi>Verona,</hi> which was no good proof of his diſſimulation. But let us go on with his ſtory.
<note n="*" place="bottom">ibid.</note> 
               <hi>The firſt of</hi> April, <hi>the Elector of</hi> Saxony <hi>beſieg'd</hi> Ausburg, <hi>which did render it ſelf the
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:33183:28"/>third day, &amp; the ſixth news came there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to</hi> Trent, <hi>&amp; that all</hi> Tirol <hi>did arm, &amp; meant to go to</hi> Inſpruc ... <hi>Therefore many of the</hi> Italian <hi>Bishops embark'd, &amp; went down the river</hi> Adice, <hi>to go to</hi> Verona, <hi>and the Proteſtants determin'd to depart.</hi> See here the true cauſe of their departure: and tell me no more, of their being either denied audience, or liberty of diſputing.</p>
            <p n="13">XIII. The place was not ſecure. A. Very true; it was far from being ſecure for the Catholicks: The Proteſtant Army forced them to ſuſpend the Council, <hi>April,</hi> 28. Neither was it any wonder, that they were ſo much afraid of their victorious arms: <hi>Soave</hi> ſays,
<note n="*" place="bottom">p 355.</note> 
               <hi>The Emperour was forced to fly by night, with all his Court from</hi> Inſpruc, &amp; <hi>to wander in the mountains of</hi> Trent, and that <hi>a few hours after,</hi> Maurice <hi>arrived there, the ſame night,</hi> &amp; <hi>made himſelf Lord of the Emperour's baggage.</hi> Conſider here, on the one ſide, how littie reaſon the Proteſtants have to complain of the choice of this place: 1. it was nigher the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of <hi>Germany,</hi> than the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks of <hi>Spain</hi> &amp; <hi>France:</hi> 2. the Pope's
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:33183:29"/>forces had no acceſs thither; 'twas in the Emperour's power: 3. the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance only, of the Proteſtant Army, was enough to fright away the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. On the other ſide, you ſee how juſtly the Pope refus'd to call a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil in any City of <hi>Germany,</hi> for fear of the Proteſtant arms. As for the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, <hi>Ut illic lites terminentur ubi exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae ſunt,</hi> 'tis underſtood of thoſe cauſes, where ſome fact is to be prov'd by witneſſes that live upon the place.</p>
            <p n="14">XIV. The Council was not free. It was call'd by the Pope: And nothing could be determin'd till the Pope ſent his inſtructions from <hi>Rome.</hi> A. If any man have a right to convocate the ſupreme Eccleſiaſtical Aſſembly, 'tis certainly He who has from God the ſupreme Eccleſiaſtical power upon earth; and this right, of calling it, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertains as manifeſtly to the Pope, as the convocation of a Provincial Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil belongs to the Metropolitan. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, <hi>Soave</hi> ſays, the Princes in the Diet of <hi>Noremberg</hi> deſired
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 31.</note> 
               <hi>that by the Pope, with conſent of the Emperour, a free Council should be intimated as ſoon as was poſſible:</hi> he ſays, the Emperour
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:33183:29"/>ſent Letters to the Diet of <hi>Spira,</hi> that
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 34.</note> 
               <hi>he was reſolved to paſs into</hi> Italy, <hi>and to</hi> Rome, <hi>to treat with the Pope, for the calling of a Council:</hi> and afterwards, under <hi>Pius</hi> IV. he ſays,
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 304.</note> 
               <hi>all Princes had agreed in demanding it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the Second part of your objec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; 'Tis certain that, if it had ſtood with the Pope's conveniency, He ought to have been preſent. In his abſence, 'twas neceſſary for the Legates, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting his perſon, to receive frequent directions from him, that they might the better ſupply the want of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. If, for this reaſon, it was lawfull to give them inſtructions before the Council began; why not, afterwards, as long as the Council was fitting? In fine, whatſoever advice came from <hi>Rome,</hi> Nothing in matter of Doctrine was determin'd, which any conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part reſiſted. <hi>Soave</hi> himſelf confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<note n="*" place="bottom">538.</note> 
               <hi>that it was a general Maxim in this Council, that to eſtablish a Decree of Reformation, a major part of voices was ſufficient; but that a Decree of Faith could not be made if a conſiderable part did contradict.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">XV. Many of the Bishops were
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:33183:30"/>Penſioners to the Pope. A. <hi>Soave</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges, that ſeveral
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 116.</note> 
               <hi>of the Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops, moved by poverty, made grievous complaints,</hi> &amp; threatned <hi>that they would depart.</hi> If therefore the Pope maintain'd ſome of them, it was a great charity done by him; a good example to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; a thing which formerly uſed to be done by the Emperours. 2. Secular Princes had more money than the Pope; and, if it had been the policy of his Holineſs, they might eaſily have countermin'd it. 3. All the Popes, in their Bulls of Convocation, deſired &amp; exhorted all Secular Princes to ſend as many of their Bishops as poſſibly they could. 4. His Penſioners were not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for him, at leaſt in the Proteſtant Controverſies; &amp; therefore this is no excuſe for the Reformation.</p>
            <p n="16">XVI. In ſome Seſſions, under <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Julius,</hi> there were ſcarce any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fides <hi>Italians.</hi> A. 1. The Council being drawn out from 1545. till 1563. &amp; actually ſitting for about four years, it cannot be rationally expected that any great frequency of Bishops should be continually preſent. 2. The diſorders, cauſed by the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:33183:30"/>by the <hi>Lutherans</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> required their Bishops reſidence to ſecure Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Religion at home; otherwiſe they would not have been abſent from the Synod. 3. The diſſentions that hapned betwixt the Pope, the Emperour, &amp; King of <hi>France,</hi> and the civil wars be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Catholicks &amp; Proteſtants, hindred the Bishops, ſometimes of one Nation, ſometimes of another, from attending the Council. 4. All this was fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenc'd, in the third &amp; laſt Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Council, under <hi>Pius</hi> IV.</p>
            <p n="17">XVII. In the end of the Council, we find 187. <hi>Italian</hi> Bishops, and all the reſt make only 83. A. 1. All theſe <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians</hi> were not of the Pope's Territory, but a great many of them ſubject to the Emperour, the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Florence,</hi> &amp; the State of <hi>Venice.</hi> In ſeveral matters they had different inſtructions, &amp; adhered to their divers intereſts, even in oppoſition to the Pope, when the Ambaſſadors of their Princes craved their aſſiſtance. <hi>Soave</hi> tells us,
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>22.</note> 
               <hi>it was publickly ſaid</hi> by the <hi>Papalins</hi> (ſo he is pleas'd to call them) <hi>that</hi> France <hi>had ever pretended to limit the Pope's power, &amp; ſubject it to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons;
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:33183:31"/>Canons;</hi> and <hi>that this opinion would be follow'd by many</hi> Italians, <hi>who, becauſe</hi> they <hi>cannot, or know not how to make uſe of the preferments of the Court, do envy thoſe that do; beſides thoſe, who are deſirous of novity, they know not why, of whom there ſeem'd to be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable number.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis no great matter, as to our preſent purpoſe, whether the Pope had all the <hi>Italian</hi> ſuffrages at his beck, or no; becauſe 'tis certain he had no need at all, of any ſuch aſſiſtance, in deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Proteſtant controverſies, in which the Bishops, of all nations, unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly agreed. See what <hi>Soave</hi> ſays, concerning the following points. Apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolical Traditions. p. 145. <hi>It was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd by all, that they should be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, as of equal authority with the Scriptures.</hi> Vulgar Edition of Scripture. p. 150. <hi>It was approved almoſt by a general conſent.</hi> &amp; p. 152. <hi>the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation being ended, the Cardinal</hi> Santa Croce <hi>aſſembled thoſe that had oppoſed the Vulgar Edition, &amp; shew'd they had no reaſon to complain, becauſe it was not prohibited, but left free, to correct it, &amp; to have recourſe to the Original; but that only it was forbid to ſay, there
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:33183:31"/>were in it Errors of Faith for which it ought to be corrected.</hi> Original Sin. p. 164. <hi>No man reſiſted the condemnation of the Articles.</hi> Juſtification &amp; Merit. p. 215. <hi>In condemning the</hi> Lutheran <hi>opinions all did agree with exquiſite U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi> Sacraments<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p. 219. <hi>All the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines agreed in affirming the number ſeven, &amp; condemning the contrary opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion as heretical.</hi> Baptiſm &amp; Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, p. 232. <hi>All parties</hi> were <hi>ſatisfied.</hi> Worship of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the Euchariſt. p. 306. <hi>All agreed.</hi> Communion under one kind. p. 306. <hi>All made uſe of long diſcourſes, but all to the ſame purpoſe.</hi> &amp; p. 485. <hi>They all agreed that there was no neceſſity, or precept, of the Cup.</hi> Tranſubſtantiation. p. 309. <hi>There was a contention between the two Schools,</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minican <hi>and</hi> Franciſcan, <hi>which troubled the Fathers, with the ſubtility &amp; ſmall fruit thereof.</hi> The <hi>Dominicans</hi> ſaid, <hi>the one ſubſtance is made of the other;</hi> The <hi>Franciſcans</hi> ſaid; <hi>the one doth ſucceed the other;</hi> Both agreed, that <hi>it is properly &amp; truly called Tranſubſtantiation:</hi> &amp; p. 310 <hi>it was determin'd in the General Congregation, to uſe an expreſſion ſo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal as might be accommodated to the meaning of both parties,</hi> without appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:33183:32"/>or condemning, either the one, or the other. Sacrifice of Maſs. p. 508. <hi>In the diſcuſſions of the Divines, all were uniform in condemning the Proteſtant opinions;</hi> although there was <hi>ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention,</hi> whether or no <hi>Chriſt</hi> at ſupper <hi>offered himſelf;</hi> p. 538. <hi>ſome ſaying, that, in regard of the three &amp; twenty contradictors, it was not lawfully deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded;</hi> and <hi>others anſwering, that an eighth part could not be called conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</hi> Auricular Confeſſion. p. 328. 329. 330. No diſagreement appears among the Prelates or Divines, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the 6.7. &amp; 8. <hi>can.</hi> of the 14. <hi>Seſſion.</hi> Extreme Unction. p. 330. <hi>The Divines ſpoke with</hi> ſome <hi>prolixity, but without any difference among themſelves.</hi> Promotion of married perſons to holy Orders. p. 698. <hi>The Fathers did uniformly, &amp; without difficulty, agree upon the negative.</hi> Matrimony. p. 730. <hi>The doctrine, &amp; anathematiſms, were read; to which all conſented.</hi> Purgatory. Invocation of Saints. p. 749. <hi>The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees were read, &amp; all approved, with great brevity &amp; little contradiction.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences. p 757. <hi>The Decrees were read, &amp; approved by all.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="207" facs="tcp:33183:32"/>
            <p n="18">XVIII. Proxies were not allowed to have deciſive votes. A. 1. There were but ſeven in the Council. 2. They had votes in conſultations, among the reſt. 3. They had no right to a deciſive vote. 4. Were it indifferently allowed, it would encourage Bishops to pretend neceſſity of their abſence.</p>
            <p n="19">XIX. All the Bishops were ſworn to the Pope, before they ſate in Council. A. 1. They never ſwore to vote againſt their judgment: They only ſwore Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical obedience &amp; fidelity to him, that is, ſuch obedience &amp; fidelity as the Canons of former Councils require,
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Bellarmin, De Concil.</hi> lib. 1, cap. 21.</note> 
               <hi>as long as he is Pope, and ſo long as he commands thoſe things, which, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to God, &amp; according to the Canons, he can command; but they do not ſwear, that they will not in Council ſay what they think; or that they will not depoſe him, if they convict him of being a Heretick.</hi> 2. An Oath taken in general terms, to defend his Canonical rights, leaves the Council in perfect liberty to examine what is Canonical, &amp; what not. 3. Without the Oath they are ſtrictly bound, by the Canons, to the ſame obedience &amp; fidelity; ſo that
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:33183:33"/>it induces no new obligation, but only confirms what was their duty before. 4. Parliament-men ſwearing fidelity to their King, according to the Laws, do not looſe the freedom of their Vote, nor the power of changing many Laws, &amp; making others, with the King's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. 5. Every Bishop in the English Church, at his conſecration, ſwears due obedience to his Archbishop &amp; his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors: Why may not Catholick Bishops ſwear as much obedience to the Pope? And what harm is there, if they take the very ſame Oath again, before they ſit in Council?</p>
            <p n="20">XX. In one of the Congregations the Bishop of <hi>Guadice</hi> was interrupted &amp; affronted; and the Cardinal of <hi>Lorain</hi> complain'd, the Council was not free. A. This hapned only once, &amp; ſatisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was preſently given <hi>Soave</hi> relates it thus.
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 593.</note> 
               <hi>The Bishop of</hi> Guadice <hi>ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the laſt
<note n="*" place="bottom">Seff. 23.</note> Canon, where it was determin'd, that Bishops call'd by the Pope are true &amp; lawfull,</hi> ſaid that <hi>there were alſo Bishops, not call'd by the Pope, nor confirm'd by him, which nevertheleſs were true &amp; lawfull. For example he brought four Suffragans,
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:33183:33"/>elected &amp; ordain'd by the Archbishop of</hi> Salzburg, <hi>who take no confirmation from the Pope. Cardinal</hi> Simoneta <hi>did not ſuffer him to proceed, ſaying, that whatſoever the Archbishop of</hi> Salzburg <hi>or other Primates did, was all by the Pope's authority. The Bishop of</hi> Cava, <hi>and</hi> two more, <hi>call'd him Schiſmatick,</hi> and <hi>ſaid he ought to be put out of the Council.</hi> Immediatly <hi>there follow'd a great noiſe among the Prelates, as well of whiſpering as of fee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, partly in offence of the Prelate that gave his voice, &amp; partly in defence. The Legates did hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeaſe the ſtir, by making others proceed, who were to ſpeak in that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation; which being ended,</hi> Lorain <hi>ſaid the Bishop had not ſpoken ill.... &amp; indeed it was found that the Bishop had not ſpoken ill, and the Canon was corrected; for whereas it ſaid, the Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops call'd by the Pope of</hi> Rome, <hi>it was altered thus; the Bishops aſſumed by the authority of the Pope of</hi> Rome..... Mantua <hi>did alſo reprehend the noiſe made with feet &amp; words, ſaying that, if hereafter they did not ſpeak with reſpect, They,</hi> the Legates, <hi>would go out of the Congregation....</hi> Lorain <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the admonition, &amp; ſaid that as
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:33183:34"/>the Legates ought not to go out of the Congregation, for any occaſion what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, ſo it was moſt juſt that the perturbers of it, should be punish'd.</hi> Here you have a full account of the whole matter. It was only a ſuddain heat, &amp; ſoon over. The publick repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, of thoſe who made a noiſe, was ſatisfaction abundantly ſufficient for what was paſt: And the altering of the Canon, according to the Bishop's ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, was a very extraordinary encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement for him, &amp; every body elſe, to ſpeak freely for the future. The Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal complain'd, before the ſatisfaction was given, &amp; the Canon alter'd, but not after. Beſides, it is not impoſſible for great men to find fault when there is but little reaſon for it. They are uſed to be humour'd, &amp; when they are croſs'd, a ſmall matter is enough for great complaints. I'l give you an inſtance out of <hi>Soave.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">p. 615.</note> Lorain <hi>and</hi> Madruccio <hi>had compoſed a form</hi> concerning <hi>Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence;</hi> The Legates <hi>approv'd it</hi> at <hi>firſt ſight;</hi> afterwards, <hi>conſulting with the Canoniſts, they diſliked one part.</hi> Lorain <hi>and</hi> Madruccio <hi>were much offended with this mutation, &amp; thought they were
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:33183:34"/>diſparag'd.</hi> Lorain <hi>ſaid, it was not a free Council.</hi> Why was not the Council free? If the <hi>form</hi> which they two had <hi>compoſed,</hi> had been blindly receiv'd without examen; if, out of compliment to them, it had been approv'd <hi>nemine contradicente;</hi> All had been well; The <hi>Council</hi> had been <hi>free</hi> enough: But becauſe ſome others took the liberty to conſider it, &amp; ſpoke their minds freely in contradicting it; therefore <hi>the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil was not free.</hi> Madruccio
<note n="*" place="bottom">ibid.</note> 
               <hi>did not forbear to ſay, there was a ſecret Council, within the Council, which did arrogate more authority.</hi> The <hi>Canoniſts,</hi> who examin'd the <hi>form</hi> which they two <hi>had compoſed,</hi> are here call'd a <hi>ſecret Council,</hi> &amp; accuſed of <hi>arrogancy;</hi> not becauſe they aſſumed <hi>more autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> but becauſe they pretended to an equal liberty of ſpeaking as freely againſt the <hi>form</hi> as others had ſpoken for it. So proud &amp; ſo ambitious we are, to have our own opinions idoliz'd, and to enlarge the empire of our fancies by enforcing them upon our neighbours; that when we meet with any oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though ever ſo reaſonable, we are ſtreightned for want of room, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:33183:35"/>for want of liberty. So, when <hi>Guzdellun</hi> came to the Council, &amp; had
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 617.</note> 
               <hi>ſeen the paſſages of one day,</hi> he <hi>ſaid, he underſtood plainly the Council was not free.</hi> What theſe paſſages were, <hi>Soave</hi> does not tell us: and, I am ſure, if any thing had hapned contrary to the liberty of the Council, the Relation of it would have been nuts to him. Since therefore your Hiſtorian leaves us to conjecture what we pleaſe; for ought I know, <hi>Guzdellun</hi> might have ſo great an opinion of himſelf, as to imagine, that, when he came to Council, the weight of his reaſons would have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently turn'd the ſcale of their delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp; that in <hi>one day</hi> he should carry all before him: but afterwards, when he <hi>plainly</hi> ſound his miſtake, and ſaw he could not in <hi>one day</hi> have all things determin'd as he pleas'd, then it was <hi>he underſtood plainly, the Council was not free.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">XXI. In the Hiſtory of the Council we find ſeveral grievous complaints of the <hi>Spanish</hi> Prelates, that they had not their liberty in propoſing &amp; determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>divine right</hi> of <hi>Reſidence.</hi> A. Let us hear their ſeveral complaints in
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:33183:35"/>order, &amp; if you believe your own Hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torian, you will find they had no reaſon to complain.</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 474.</note> They <hi>complain'd of the Pope for holding the Council in ſervitude, to which he ought to leave free power to handle &amp; determine all things, and not to meddle himſelf.</hi> A. This laſt clauſe is manifeſtly unreaſonable; Why should not he <hi>meddle</hi> as well as they? Pray, read <hi>Soave,</hi> &amp; ſee in what manner he <hi>meddled</hi> with them.
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 470.</note> 
               <hi>He commended them for ſpeaking according to their Conſcience.... He complain'd of thoſe who referr'd themſelves unto him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Council was aſſembled that every one may deliver his opinion...
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 471.</note> He was pleas'd that every one should deliver his opinion freely... but ſaid, it was a ſtrange thing, that he who was Head of the Church, and other Prelates, who have voice in Council, may not be inform'd of what is handled, and ſpeak their opinion... whereas, on the other ſide, it is plain that ſo many Prelates come to</hi> Trent <hi>with commiſſion from their Princes, according to which they proceed; &amp; that the Ambaſſadors by Letters &amp; perſwaſions do compell them
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:33183:36"/>to follow the intereſts of their Maſters, &amp; yet, for all this, no man ſays, that</hi> therefore <hi>the Council is not free. This He amplified with much vehemency,</hi> &amp; certainly with a great deal of reaſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In their Letter to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> They
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 515.</note> 
               <hi>complain'd of the Legates</hi> for not ſuffering <hi>the point</hi> of Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence <hi>to be concluded, before they could have</hi> an <hi>anſwer from</hi> Rome. A. They themſelves aquainted the King with theſe matters: Why might not the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates inform the Pope? They
<note n="*" place="bottom">ibid.</note> 
               <hi>beſeech'd his Majeſty to conſult with godly men about this Article:</hi> Why might not the Pope <hi>conſult with godly men,</hi> as well as He? They
<note n="*" place="bottom">ibid.</note> 
               <hi>aſſur'd themſelves that, after mature deliberation, He would favour their opinion:</hi> Whether <hi>He would</hi> or not, was more than they could tell, till they had an anſwer; &amp; Why might not an <hi>anſwer</hi> be expected from <hi>Rome,</hi> as well as from <hi>Madrid?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. In the ſame Letter, they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd
<note n="*" place="bottom">ibid.</note> 
               <hi>that there was no liberty in the Council,</hi> becauſe <hi>the</hi> Italians <hi>did overcome with plurality of voices.</hi> A. In the ſame Letter they tell the King, <hi>that two thirds of the Prelates did deſire
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:33183:36"/>the Definition,</hi> &amp; <hi>that all the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors did favour the Truth herein.</hi> If <hi>two thirds</hi> were <hi>for</hi> them, &amp; only <hi>one</hi> third <hi>againſt</hi> them, can you tell me how twas poſſible for them to be <hi>overcome with plurality of voices?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. They complain'd that
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 475.</note> 
               <hi>when a propoſition is made in which</hi> 70. <hi>Bishops do uniformly agree, they are hindred even to ſpeak thereof.</hi> A. Who hindred them? <hi>Soave</hi> tells us, that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> wrote to his Ambaſſador to let
<note place="bottom">p. 505.</note> 
               <hi>his Prelates</hi> know, <hi>He thought the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration did not befit the preſent time, &amp; therefore wisht them to deſiſt;</hi> &amp; that the French Ambaſſadors wrote to their Maſter, how little hopes they had of
<note place="bottom">p 507.</note> 
               <hi>reforming the Court</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe <hi>the</hi> Spaniards, <hi>who were very zealous for the Reformation,</hi> were <hi>cooled, &amp; put in fear, by the reprehenſion of their King.</hi> But the Pope, inſtead of <hi>wishing them to deſiſt,
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 470,</note> commended them for ſpeaking according to their Conſcience.</hi> Neither did the Legates <hi>with them to deſiſt:</hi> They only
<note place="bottom">p. 473.</note> 
               <hi>anſwer'd, that the Article was not fit to be propos'd in that Seſſion, but that it should be done in time convenient:</hi> which was ſo far from
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:33183:37"/>being any <hi>hindrance</hi> of their <hi>ſpeaking,</hi> that upon the very next occaſion
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 477.</note> 
               <hi>they began to diſcourſe again of it ...</hi> &amp; <hi>the heat grew ſo great, that ſome of the Ultramontans threatned to proteſt &amp; depart;</hi> and perhaps would have departed, had not the Ambaſſadors pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified them. So unreaſonably jealous men are of their Liberty, that, even when they take too much, they think they have too little.</p>
            <p n="22">XXII. <hi>Andrew Dudith,</hi> Bishop of <hi>Five-churches,</hi> ſent by the Emperour <hi>Ferdinand</hi> as his Ambaſſador to the Council, writes afterwards a Letter to <hi>Maximilian</hi> II. in which he complains that <hi>the votes were not weighed but numbred,</hi> that <hi>the Pope had a hundred for one,</hi> that <hi>the Holy Ghoſt was ſent from</hi> Rome <hi>in a Poſtillons Cloak bag...</hi> O <hi>monſtrous extraordinary madneſs! Nothing could be ratified which the Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops did decree, unleſs the Pope made himſelf the Author of it.</hi> A. 1. His Lordship was perhaps a little angry when he wrote this Letter; &amp; an angry man, you know, is apt to talk ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagantly: <hi>Iratus nil niſimonſtra loqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> What would you ſay, if a <hi>Member</hi>
               <pb n="217" facs="tcp:33183:37"/>of the <hi>Houſe,</hi> a friend of yours, should complain at the ſame rate; <hi>O monſtrous extraordinary madneſs! nothing could be ratified in Parliament which the Lords &amp; Commons did decree, unleſs his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty were pleas'd to give his Royal Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</hi> Would you take this for the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of his Reaſon or his Paſſion ? 2. Although he ſeem'd a <hi>Catholick</hi> when he ſate in Council, yet he declared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> ſoon after; which is another motive to ſuſpect he makes the worſt of things. 3. 'Tis remarkable that his conceit of the <hi>Cloak-bag</hi> was firſt made uſe of in <hi>Trent,</hi> when the Legates, finding
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 464.</note> 
               <hi>a fourth part only</hi> againſt the <hi>divine right</hi> of <hi>Reſidence,</hi> &amp; obſerving how
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 465.</note> 
               <hi>they came to words of ſome bitterneſs,</hi> they <hi>exhorted the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to modeſty, gave them leave to depart,</hi> &amp; <hi>agreed to give the Pope an account of all.</hi> This did not pleaſe the <hi>Spaniards:</hi> but, why Bishop <hi>Dudith</hi> should find fault, I cannot underſtand. <hi>Soave</hi> tells us, he employ'd his Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick to oppoſe the Bishop of <hi>Aiace,</hi> &amp; to prove that it was lawfull for Bishops to
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 457.</note> 
               <hi>buſie themſelves in the Courts of Princes, &amp; in the Affairs of the world,</hi>
               <pb n="218" facs="tcp:33183:38"/>as <hi>being Judges, Chancellors, Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Counſellors, Treaſurers,</hi> &amp;c. which was, as <hi>Soave</hi> obſerves, a plain
<note n="*" place="bottom">p 458.</note> 
               <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting of thoſe who thought that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence was</hi> de jure divino. Pray, help me now, if you can, to reconcile your Friend's Hiſtory with the Bishop's Letter.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In his <hi>Letter,</hi> we find him very bitter againſt the <hi>hireling Bishops,</hi> the <hi>images of</hi> Daedalus <hi>that mov'd by nerves which were none of their own,</hi> the <hi>country bag-pipes which could not ſpeak, but as breath was put into them.</hi> And who would think, after all this, that in your <hi>Hiſtory</hi> we should find him among theſe very <hi>Papalins,</hi> &amp; as buſie as the beſt of them, giving his ſuffrage with them, againſt the Decree of Reſidence? Who <hi>hired</hi> him? what <hi>nerves mov'd</hi> him to ſide with them? Whoſe <hi>breath</hi> was <hi>put into him</hi> to make him <hi>ſpeak</hi> in favour of them? 2. In his <hi>Letter,</hi> he complains <hi>the votes were not weigh'd but num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred:</hi> And, in your <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Legates, not to determine a point of Doctrine, which
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 464.</note> 
               <hi>a fourth part did diſlike,</hi> makes it plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear,
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:33183:38"/>that the <hi>votes</hi> of Bishop <hi>Dudith</hi>'s party <hi>were not</hi> only <hi>numbred</hi> but <hi>weigh'd.</hi> 3. If we believe his <hi>Letter, the Pope had an hundred for one, &amp; if thoſe had not been enough, he could have</hi> ſent <hi>a thouſand more</hi> in a Cloak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bag <hi>to have helpt in time of need:</hi> And, if <hi>Soave</hi>'s <hi>Hiſtory</hi> may be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd, the <hi>Papalins</hi> in this occaſion were
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>a fourth part only;</hi> They had <hi>three</hi> for <hi>one</hi> againſt them. How to accord theſe matters, I confeſs, I am at a loſs: when you have nothing elſe to do, you may try you skill at lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Mean time, I can diſcover no other reaſon, he had to quarrel with the Council, but that it was a Body with a Head. He had a mortal aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion againſt the Pope: And, whether the <hi>Papalins</hi> were for <hi>Dudith</hi> or againſt him, 'twas all the ſame: If his Holineſs were conſulted, he had not pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to ſupport it without exclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, O <hi>monſtrous extraordinary mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs!</hi> What shall you &amp; I call <hi>Paſſion,</hi> if this muſt paſs for <hi>Reaſon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">XXIII. <hi>Soave</hi> himſelf, after having related the manner how the Council was transferr'd from <hi>Trent</hi> to <hi>Bolonia,</hi>
               <pb n="220" facs="tcp:33183:39"/>defies any man
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 251.</note> 
               <hi>to ſay what liberty they had.</hi> A. Let us hear him tell his own ſtory; take it in pieces; &amp; ſee whether <hi>Soave</hi> be not able to anſwer himſelf.</p>
            <p>The Article of <hi>Reſidence</hi> being ſet on foot by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> together with ſeveral other points of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the Legates wrote to <hi>Paul</hi> III. that
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 239.</note> 
               <hi>the Prelates did every day take more liberty, not refraining to ſpeak of the Cardinals without reſpect, and with ſmall reverence of his Holineſs: that hereafter it would be hard to keep them in order, becauſe they had many private aſſemblies among themſelves... &amp; that it was not likely they would be ſo bold, without they were upheld, &amp; perhaps incited, by ſome great Prince.</hi> The Pope <hi>conſiderd, that all the Reformation aim'd to reſtrain</hi> his <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, &amp; to enlarge the power of Bishops ...</hi> that
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 241.</note> 
               <hi>the</hi> Spaniards, <hi>are a wiſe Nation who ſtep not one foot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward without looking a great way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them ... He thought that this webb was ſecretly ſpun by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, in regard his Ambaſſador did dayly treat with them ... He weigh'd
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:33183:39"/>above all, his words uſed to the Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio, that he had no greater enemy than the Pope. He fear'd that when he had eſtablisht an abſolute authority in</hi> Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many, <hi>he would think to do alike in</hi> Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>making uſe of the Council to ſuppreſs the Papacy ... To tranſlate it to a place where he had</hi> more <hi>abſolute authority, ſeem'd the beſt Counſel ...</hi> Bolonia <hi>ſeem'd the beſt place ... &amp; he reſolv'd to cauſe it to done by the Legates, by the Authority given them in the Bull</hi> of <hi>Tranſlation. Being thus reſolv'd, he ſent a private Gentleman, with Letters of credit, to do this Ambaſſage to both the Legates ...
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 248.</note> The</hi> 21. <hi>of</hi> April, <hi>the Popes meſſenger appear'd &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd to the Legates his Credence ...</hi> At this time, <hi>it hapned fitly, that many in the families of the Prelates were ſick ... the air had been moiſt many days before ... the Phyſicians ſpoke as if the diſeaſe were contagious ... it was reported that the neighbour places would have no commerce with the City.. The Phyſicians were examin'd,</hi> &amp; a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs</hi> made <hi>concerning the Peſtilent infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity ... the Proceſs was proſecuted until the</hi> 8. <hi>day, when news came that</hi> Vero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:33183:40"/>
               <hi>would trafick no more with them... Therefore, the</hi> 9. <hi>day, a general Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was held,</hi> &amp; <hi>Monte</hi> took this oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to <hi>propoſe the Tranſlation of the Council, &amp; cauſe the Pope's Bull to be read ... The Emperour's Prelates anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werd that the diſeaſe &amp; dangers were not ſo great,</hi> and look'd upon it as
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 250.</note> 
               <hi>a pretence. The next day a Congregation was call'd to conſult upon the ſame matter. It was found that</hi> 11. <hi>Prelates were already parted; &amp; they began to ſpeak of the place, whither to go. That it should be in</hi> Germany <hi>all did abhor. It could not be in the State of any Prince, becauſe they had treated with none. The Legates propos'd</hi> Bolonia ... <hi>The Imperialiſts did contradict: but the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor part conſented... The next day, the Seſſion being held, &amp; the Decree read.</hi> 25. <hi>Bishops &amp;</hi> 3. <hi>Generals did aſſent, but the Cardinal</hi> Pacceco &amp; 17. <hi>other Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops oppoſed. Among thoſe that conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, there was not one of the Emperour's ſubjects,</hi> &amp;c. In this Relation I have purpoſely omitted ſeveral clauſes, not only for brevity ſake, but becauſe I cannot think that any man is oblig'd to believe ſuch abuſive conſtructions &amp;
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:33183:40"/>conjectures, without better proof than <hi>Soave</hi>'s bare word for't. And now you may here obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. How little power the Pope had in <hi>Trent,</hi> ſince he thought it not fit to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in this buſineſs, &amp; ſince the Legates were in great danger of finding an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuperable oppoſition, had not the ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <hi>hapned fitly</hi> for the purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How much power the Emperour had over all his Prelates. <hi>Soave</hi> ſays,
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 250.</note> 
               <hi>the Imperialiſts were commanded by the Emperour's Ambaſſador, not to depart, until his Majeſty were inform'd, &amp; gave them order.</hi> He gives an account after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of their
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 253.</note> 
               <hi>remaining in</hi> Trent <hi>by expreſs order from the Emperour,</hi> and obſtinately
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 260.</note> 
               <hi>refuſing to go</hi> or ſend <hi>to</hi> Bolonia, <hi>to acknowledg the Council;</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Pope
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 262.</note> 
               <hi>pray'd them,</hi> either <hi>to come, or ſend Proctors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Pope <hi>praying</hi> on the one ſide, the Emperour <hi>commanding</hi> on the other; the <hi>prayers</hi> being ſlighted, the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands</hi> being punctually obey'd; 'tis eaſy to conclude, which was moſt likely to reſtrain the liberty of the Council, when return'd to <hi>Trent:</hi> eſpecially, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Emperour's being then
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 283.</note> 
               <hi>King
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:33183:41"/>of</hi> Spain <hi>and</hi> Naples, <hi>Prince of the</hi> Low-Countries, <hi>&amp; having other adherencies in</hi> Italy.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Emperour's Proteſtation, read by <hi>Valaſco</hi> in the Council of <hi>Bolonia,</hi> shews plainly what liberty might be expected from him, who aſſumed to himſelf the arbitrary priviledg of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 263.</note> 
               <hi>opinions of the Fathers,</hi> &amp; determining <hi>who did ſpeak for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake,</hi> &amp;
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 264.</note> 
               <hi>who, though not ſo many in number, ought to be preferr'd, as more wiſe.</hi> At this rate, All the other Prelates of the Univerſal Church, what would they ſignifie? Though they were ten for one againſt them, 'tis no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; the Prelates of the Emperour muſt always be ſuppos'd to be the men <hi>who ſpeak for conſcience ſake,</hi> the men <hi>who are more wiſe,</hi> &amp; <hi>therefore</hi> the men <hi>who ought to be preferr'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. If the Pope, having juſt reaſon to ſuſpect the future ſervitude of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, endeavour'd to prevent the great diſorders, which might happen in <hi>Trent,</hi> by giving ſecret inſtructions to his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates, to transfer the Synod to <hi>Bolonia,</hi> Who can blame him?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Soave</hi> ſays,
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 251.</note> 
               <hi>it ſcandaliz'd every
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:33183:41"/>one.</hi> And yet I know not why they should be ſcandaliz'd, any more than you &amp; I were, when King <hi>Charles</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd the Parliament from <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> to <hi>Oxford.</hi> He goes on, <hi>if the two Legates could command all the Prelates to part from Trent, &amp; compel them by cenſures, Let any man ſay that can, what liberty they had.</hi> 'Tis eaſily <hi>ſaid;</hi> They had, all of them, liberty to vote freely according to their conſcience; The Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates commanded no body; The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was put to Votes, &amp; the Majority carried it: And now, <hi>Let any man ſay, that can, what liberty they</hi> wanted.</p>
            <p n="24">XXIV. This is not all. The ſame Author (having rehears'd how the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers at <hi>Bolonia</hi> unanimouſly agreed, not to <hi>treat</hi> of <hi>returning</hi> to <hi>Trent,</hi> till <hi>thoſe, who remain'd there, firſt</hi> came to <hi>Bolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, to unite with the reſt, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg the Council;</hi>) concludes with theſe words,
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Spirit which was wont to move the Legates to think as the Pope did, &amp; the Bishops to believe as the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates, did work as formerly it had done.</hi> A. Have but patience to conſider well what <hi>Soave</hi> himſelf has ſaid elſewhere;
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 260.</note>
               <pb n="226" facs="tcp:33183:42"/>and, if you believe him, you'l believe he is miſtaken here.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Pray what ſpirit <hi>formerly</hi> mov'd all the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> to ſtay behind at <hi>Treat,</hi> when the reſt went with the Legates to <hi>Bolonia?</hi> In <hi>Trent</hi> the Bishops <hi>formerly</hi> had <hi>diſagreed</hi> about <hi>going</hi> thence: Afterwards in <hi>Bolonia</hi> they all <hi>agreed</hi> about <hi>ſtaying</hi> there. And, truly, if <hi>Soave</hi> could have perſwaded us that Concord &amp; Diſcord are all one, he might eaſily have made us believe that in <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia, The ſpirit workt as formerly it had done.</hi> Befides, Theſe of <hi>Bolonia</hi> were the major part, &amp; tis no wonder they perſever'd in their reſolutions: Thoſe of <hi>Trent</hi> were the leſſer part, which ought to have ſubmitted; and yet, although the Pope exhorted them to their duty, &amp;
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 262.</note> 
               <hi>prayd them,</hi> either <hi>to come,</hi> or <hi>to ſend Proctors,</hi> they ſtill remain'd as obſtinate as the others were conſtant. And, I muſt needs ſay, betwixt you &amp; me, if your Friend <hi>Soave</hi> had been impartial, he would never have committed ſuch a miſtake in the misplacing of his jeſt: He would have told us (with a great deal of Truth, &amp; without appearance of impiety) that <hi>The ſpirit which
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:33183:42"/>was wont to move the</hi> Ambaſſadors <hi>to think as the</hi> Emperour <hi>did, &amp; the Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops to believe as the</hi> Ambaſſadors, <hi>did work as formerly it had done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. If, by this conceit, he would inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate that the Legates were always <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palins;</hi> I muſt beg your pardon, if I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to prove it notoriouſly falſe, by his own Hiſtory. He often tells us, how the proceedings of the Legates were contrary to the inſtructions they receiv'd from <hi>Rome.
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 470.</note> The Court did generally complain of all the Legates, for ſuffering the Article</hi> of Reſidence <hi>to be propoſed... becauſe they had an example of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, which this diſpute cauſed in the firſt Council.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Although I do not find that, in this Council, the Ambaſſadors of any Secular Prince ever diſſented among themſelves, in things relating to their Maſter's intereſts; yet <hi>Soave</hi> himſelf aſſures us, that, in this caſe of Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, only two of the Legates were for the <hi>Papalins,</hi> &amp; three againſt them:
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 464.</note> Altemps <hi>follow'd</hi> Simoneta, <hi>and the other two adhered to</hi> Mantua. By which you may clearly ſee that your Hiſtorian was grievouſly miſtaken,
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:33183:43"/>when he ſaid, <hi>the ſpirit was wont to move the Legates to think as the Pope did;</hi> for, by his own computation, there were three to two among them, who were <hi>moved</hi> to <hi>think</hi> quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <p n="4">4. You remember the conteſt which aroſe, concerning the third Convocation of the Council: The <hi>Spanish</hi> Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 473.</note> 
               <hi>made earneſt ſuit in the King's name, that it might be declared a Continuation of the Council, begun un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> Paul III. <hi>&amp; proſecuted under</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius. <hi>He was aſſiſted by the</hi> Spanish <hi>Prelates, and others who follow'd them ...</hi> On the other ſide, <hi>the Emperour's Ambaſſadors uſed ſtrong perſuaſions to the contrary, ſaying they would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently depart &amp; proteſt...</hi> The Legates were divided: Seripando <hi>had no other aim, but that it should be determin'd to be a Continuation... but</hi> Mantua <hi>did conſtantly reſiſt...</hi> Here you may take notice once more, that <hi>Soave</hi>'s jeſts are not always true ones: <hi>The Spirit did</hi> not <hi>move</hi> Mantua <hi>to think as the Pope did:</hi> for when the
<note n="*" place="bottom">p 474.</note> 
               <hi>news came to</hi> Rome, <hi>the Pope was ſorry to ſee that Cardinal joynd with the</hi> Spaniards <hi>in
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:33183:43"/>the point of</hi> Reſidence, <hi>and oppoſite to them in the</hi> Continuation; <hi>which was to croſs him in all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Afterwards
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 478.</note> 
               <hi>the Pope reſolv'd that the</hi> Continuation <hi>should be declar'd, let the Emperour do what he could; and diſpatch'd a Currier to</hi> Trent <hi>with this Commiſſion.</hi> If <hi>the Spirit had been wont to move the Legates to think as the Pope did,</hi> why dos <hi>Soave</hi> tell us that, this Commiſſion <hi>being arrived the ſecond of</hi> June, they <hi>all reſolv'd uniformly to inform the Pope better,</hi> &amp; <hi>shew him the impoſſibility to perform his Order?</hi> Why dos he tell us, that <hi>the next day... at night, a Currier came with Letters, that his Holineſs did refer all to the wiſdom &amp; judgment of the Legates?</hi> I might cite you a great deal more, to this purpoſe; but this is enough to shew, 1. that the Legates ſpoke freely their minds, and acted according to their Conſcience; 2. that the Pope did not endeavour to hold the Council in ſervitude.</p>
            <p n="25">XXV. Nothing could be debated but what the Legates propoſed; the Pope's Commiſſions running with this clauſe, <hi>proponentibus Legatis.</hi> A. 1. At leaſt the Council voted freely upon the matters
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:33183:44"/>which were propoſed. 2. In great Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies ſuch a method is neceſſary, to avoid confuſion. 3. It was at length
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Seſſ</hi> 24. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. <hi>de Reform.</hi>
               </note> declar'd, that the clauſe was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted with <hi>deſign of changing the uſual method of treating matters in General Councils;</hi> and then, <hi>Soave</hi> ſays,
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 728.</note> 
               <hi>The difficulty receiv'd an end, with ſatisfaction of all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You that have read <hi>Soave,</hi> may eaſily remember a great many paſſages, in which the Prelates over-ruled the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates, &amp; forced them to debate things which they had no mind to. 1. This clauſe, <hi>proponentibus Legatis,</hi> was
<note n="*" place="bottom">ibid.</note> 
               <hi>much agitated:</hi> 2. The Title of the Council, <hi>Repreſenting the Univerſal Church:</hi> 3. The <hi>divine right</hi> of <hi>Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence:</hi> 4. The <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of <hi>Bishops</hi> being <hi>de jure divino:</hi> 5. The general Reformation of the Church: which point might have been pusht perhaps too far, if the Legates had not wiſely counterpoiſed it, with propoſing a ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Reformation of Secular Princes. 6. Concerning the grant of the Cup, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Emperour, you read in <hi>Soave,</hi> that
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 530.</note> 
               <hi>the Legates were deſirous to give him ſatisfaction, but could not,
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:33183:44"/>becauſe the party of the negative pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall'd.</hi> 7. About admitting the Proteſtant Divines to diſputation, you find that
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 343.</note> 
               <hi>this opinion was readily embrac'd, firſt by the</hi> Dutch, <hi>then by the</hi> Spanish <hi>Prelates, &amp; at laſt ſomewhat coldly by the</hi> Italians, <hi>the Legate remaining im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable, and shewing plainly that he ſtood quiet, being forc'd by neceſſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Give me leave to add one inſtance more, and if you are not fully ſatisfied with it, I shall know what to think of you. Read <hi>Soave,</hi> p. 498. &amp; 499. and obſerve, 1. how boldly the Bishops of <hi>Veglia</hi> and <hi>Sidonia</hi> ſpoke their minds concerning the corruptions of <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp; Reformation of the Pope himſelf; 2. how moderately <hi>the Legates &amp; other Papalins</hi> diſcourſed about it, when, <hi>the Congregation being ended, they remain'd in the place together</hi> to conſider the <hi>holdneſs,</hi> &amp; <hi>too much licence,</hi> of the Prelates, in <hi>broaching new mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this occaſion <hi>Caſtello,</hi> who had been Speaker under <hi>Julius,</hi> told them that Cardinal <hi>Creſcentius</hi> was uſed <hi>to interrupt them</hi> &amp; <hi>ſometimes impoſe them ſilence.</hi> But the Cardinal of <hi>Varmia</hi> sharply reprehended this practiſe, &amp;
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:33183:45"/>
               <hi>ſaid, that Nothing is more neceſſary to a Chriſtian Synod than Liberty; and that, reading the Councils of the better times, one shall find contentions &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords in the heginnings of them, even in the preſence of the Emperours, which notwithſtanding did, in the end, turn, by the aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt, into a marvellous concord; and that was the miracle which did pacifie the world. He ſaid, there were infinite contentions in the</hi> Nicene <hi>Council, &amp; moſt exorbitant in the</hi> Epheſine, <hi>and therefore no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if there were now ſome diverſity of opinions civilly carried, which he that would reſiſt by human &amp; violent means, will let the world know that the Council is not free, &amp; take from it all reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; that it is good to refer the cauſe unto God, who will govern Councils, &amp; moderate thoſe who are aſſembled in his name. The Cardinal of</hi> Mantua <hi>approv'd</hi> this <hi>opinion, &amp; diſliked the proceeding of</hi> Creſcentius, <hi>but ſaid, it was not contrary to the liberty of the Council to moderate abuſes with Decrees, preſcribing the order &amp; time of ſpeaking, &amp; diſtributing to every one his own part.</hi> This <hi>was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> by <hi>Varmia,</hi> &amp; <hi>they agreed to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="233" facs="tcp:33183:45"/>
            <p n="26">XXVI. Notwithſtanding all this, the Legates would not give leave to propoſe the Article concerning the Inſtitution of Bishops.
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 550.</note> 
               <hi>Granata, Braganza, Meſſina,</hi> &amp; <hi>Segovia,</hi> having <hi>obtain'd audience of the Legates, deſired that they might handle the Articles, that Bishops are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by Chriſt, &amp; are Superior to Prieſts</hi> jure divino. <hi>The Legates, after they had conferr'd together, anſwerd, that it was fit to declare, a Bishop is ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior, but
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 551.</note> that it was not neceſſary to ſay,</hi> quo jure. <hi>Granata</hi> replyd, <hi>that there was a Controverſy, and that, if the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines did diſpute it, the neceſſity of deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this point would be known. The Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates would not conſent by any means.</hi> A. 1. They did not abſolutely forbid the debating of this matter. 2. After expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of the contentions about Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, they could not but foreſee that this diſpute, ſo much connected with the other, might occaſion greater diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, of which they would have been guilty, had they given leave: &amp; therefore they
<note n="*" place="bottom">ibid.</note> 
               <hi>would not conſent by any means.</hi> 3. The Divines &amp; Prelates freely took leave, though it was not given them; &amp; never ſpoke more boldly, than they did
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:33183:46"/>upon this ſubject. If you will not believe me, believe your friend <hi>Soave:</hi> Read what follows, &amp; believe your own eyes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Michael Orencuſpe,</hi> a Divine of the Bishop of <hi>Pampelona,</hi> argued,
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 558.</note> 
               <hi>that howſoever it be true and certain, that Bishops are ſuperior</hi> jure Pontificio, <hi>yet the Lutherans are not in this regard to be condemn'd for Hereticks, becauſe that cannot be an Article of Faith, which is grounded only upon the Law of man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </note> John Fonſeca <hi>a Divine of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of</hi> Granata <hi>follow'd, ſaying, it neither was, nor could be forbidden to ſpeak of it. For the Article being propos'd to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſs'd, whether it be heretical or no, it is neceſſary to underſtand whether it be againſt Faith; againſt which it cannot be, if it do not repugn to the Law of God.</hi> He ſaid <hi>that if the Pope be inſtituted by</hi> Chriſt, <hi>becauſe he hath ſaid to</hi> Peter, Feed my Lambs, <hi>Bishops are likewiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted</hi> by him, <hi>becauſe he hath ſaid alike to all the Apoſtles,</hi> as my Father hath ſent me, ſo I ſend you. <hi>And, if the Pope be Succeſſor of</hi> S. Peter, <hi>the Bishops are Succeſſors of the</hi> Apoſtles; <hi>which</hi> he prov'd by <hi>many Authorities out of the Fathers. He added, that to be confirm'd
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:33183:46"/>or created by the Pope, did not conclude, that they were not inſtituted by</hi> Chriſt, <hi>or had not authority from him. For the Pope himſelf is created by the Cardinals, and yet hath his authority from</hi> Chriſt: <hi>So the Bishops receive the Dioceſs from the Pope, &amp; authority from</hi> Chriſt. <hi>Their Superiority over Prieſts he prov'd to be</hi> jure divino, <hi>by authority of many Fathers, who ſay that Bishops ſucceed the Apoſtles, &amp; Prieſts the ſeventy two Diſciples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Antony Groſſetus <hi>inſiſted upon</hi> the ſame point.
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 559.</note> 
               <hi>He ſaid it was neceſſary to declare, that Bishops have not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, for their Office, from men; for ſo they would, be Hirelings, to whom the Lambs do not belong, becauſe the man, who had committed the care unto them, being ſatisfied, they had no more to think on ....</hi> In the end, he excuſed himſelf, <hi>that he had ſpoken without premedita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ...</hi> not remembring that <hi>that point was forbidden to be ſpoke of.</hi> Here it is that <hi>Soave</hi> would make us believe, that <hi>Groſſetus</hi> fear'd <hi>ſome bad encounter,</hi> but, I am ſure, if any <hi>bad encounter</hi> had ever hapned to him, upon this account, <hi>Soave</hi> would have taken care to let us know it. Have but a little patience to obſerve how freely &amp; boldly the Bishops deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:33183:47"/>their opinions in the following Congregations, and then Pl give you leave to tell me, if you can, what <hi>bad encounter</hi> they fear'd.</p>
            <p>The Archbishop of <hi>Granata</hi> ſaid,
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 565.</note> 
               <hi>They muſt needs declare both theſe two points, that is, that Bishops are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted</hi> jure divino, <hi>and are</hi> jure divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no <hi>ſuperior to Prieſts: And he confirm'd his opinion at large, with many reaſons, arguments, &amp; authorities...He cited Pope</hi> Eleutherius, <hi>who, in an epiſtle to the Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops of</hi> France, <hi>wrote, that</hi> Chriſt <hi>had committed the Church Univerſal to them.</hi> He added, <hi>that</hi> Ambroſe <hi>upon the Epiſtle to the</hi> Corinthians <hi>ſaith, that the Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hop holdeth the place of</hi> Chriſt, <hi>&amp; is Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car of the Lord ...</hi> that <hi>there are extant Epiſtles of</hi> Cyprian <hi>to</hi> Fabianus, Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius, Lucius, <hi>and</hi> Stephanus, <hi>Popes, where he giveth them the title of Brothers; and of</hi> Auſtin, <hi>written in his own name, &amp; of the Bishops of</hi> Africa, <hi>in which the Popes</hi> Innocentius <hi>and</hi> Bonifacius <hi>are likewiſe call'd Brothers;</hi> &amp;, <hi>which is moſt plain, not only in the Epiſtles of thoſe two Saints, but of many others, the Pope is call'd</hi> Colleague ... that <hi>it is againſt the nature of a Colledge to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of perſons of divers kinds... In this
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:33183:47"/>Colledg of Bishops, the Pope is Head; but, for edification only ... that</hi> S. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory <hi>ſaith in his epiſtle to</hi> Johannes Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racuſanus, <hi>that when a Bishop is in a fault, he is ſubject to the Apoſtolick See, but otherwiſe all are equal by reaſon of humility, which Chriſtian Humility is never ſeparated from the Truth. He inveigh'd againſt thoſe Theologues who ſaid, that S. Peter had ordain'd the other Apoſtles Bishops ...
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 566.</note> He jeſted at thoſe Divines who had ſaid, that all the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles were inſtituted by</hi> Chriſt, <hi>and made equal in authority, but that it was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal in them, &amp; ought not to paſs to their Succeſſors, except that of</hi> S. Peter; <hi>asking them, as if they had been preſent, with what ground, authority, or reaſon, they were induced to make ſuch a bold affirmation, invented within theſe fifty years only, expreſsly contrary to the Scripture, in which</hi> Chriſt <hi>ſaid to all the Apoſtles,</hi> I will be with you untill the end of the world, <hi>which words, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they cannot be expounded of their particular perſons only, muſt be neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily underſtood of the ſucceſſion of all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="bottom">p. 567.</note> 
               <hi>The Archbishop of</hi> Braga <hi>prov'd at large, the Inſtitution of Bishops</hi> de jure divino. <hi>He ſaid, that the Pope cannot take
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:33183:48"/>from Bishops the Authority given them in their conſecration, which doth contain in it the power, not only of Order but of Juriſdiction ... that to Titular Bishops a City is allotted, which would not be neceſſary, if the Epiſcopal Order could ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt without Juriſdiction.</hi> He was follow'd by the Bishops of <hi>Segovia,</hi> of <hi>Segna,</hi> &amp; others, who ſpoke as boldy as himſelf, not fearing any <hi>bad encounter;</hi> and <hi>Soave</hi> ſays
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 569.</note> 
               <hi>almoſt the half were of that opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Afterwards,
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 577.</note> 
               <hi>to quench the boyling heat of the controverſy about the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Bishops, that it might not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, by means of ſo many who were prepar'd to contradict</hi> Laynez. <hi>they would not hold any Congregation for many days.</hi> And yet they were ſo far from fearing any <hi>bad encounter,</hi> that <hi>almoſt every day
<note n="*" place="bottom">p 578.</note> three or four of them joyn'd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; went to ſome of the Legates to renew the inſtance. And, one day, the Bishop of</hi> Guadice, <hi>with four others,</hi> told them, among other things, that
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>as a Prince dos inſtitute, in a City, a Judge of the firſt inſtante, &amp; a Judge of Appeal, who though he be ſuperior, yet cannot take authority from the other,
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:33183:48"/>nor uſurp the cauſes belonging to him: ſo</hi> Chriſt <hi>in the Church hath inſtituted all Bishops, &amp; the Pope ſuperior, in whom the Supreme Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction was; yet ſo, that others had theirs depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on Chriſt alone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After all this, the Bishop of <hi>Segovia,</hi> when the Prelates met again in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, argued
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 582.</note> 
               <hi>that it was decided in the Congregations under</hi> Julius III. <hi>that Bishops are inſtituted</hi> jure divino; <hi>though</hi> it was <hi>not publisht in Seſſion, by reaſon of the ſuddain diſſolution of the Council... The Cardinal of</hi> Mantua <hi>cauſed the Acts of that time to be ſearch'd, &amp; that to be read by the Secretary, which was then defined to be published... Three Heads of Doctrine were then compoſed,</hi> and in <hi>the third,</hi> which was of <hi>Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> it was ſaid, <hi>The Holy Synod doth teach, that thoſe are not to be hearkned unto, who ſay that Bishops are not inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted</hi> jure divino, <hi>it appearing manifeſtly by the words of the Ghoſpel, that</hi> Chriſt <hi>our Lord hath himſelf call'd the Apoſtles, &amp; promoted them to the degree of Apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, into whoſe place the Bishops are ſubrogated; neither ought we to think that this ſo eminent &amp; neceſſary a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, hath been brought into the Church
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:33183:49"/>by human inſtitution.</hi> There were <hi>alſo eight Canons,</hi> the <hi>laſt whereof ſaid</hi> thus: <hi>He that shall ſay, that Bishops are not inſtituted</hi> Jure divino, <hi>or are not Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to Prieſts, or have not power to ordain, or that this doth belong to Prieſts, Let him be Anathema.</hi> This <hi>the Cardinal of</hi> Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua <hi>interpreted, only of the power of Order, &amp;</hi> the Bishop of <hi>Segovia</hi> underſtood it <hi>of All, which containeth Order &amp; Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction;</hi> and, though <hi>he anſwer'd reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently in appearance, there paſt ſo many replies, that they were forced to break up the Congregation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Cardinal of <hi>Lorain</hi> came to <hi>Trent,</hi> he told the Cardinal of <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua,</hi> he
<note n="*" place="bottom">p 583.</note> 
               <hi>would not be curious in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable queſtions;</hi> that, <hi>for his own part, he was more inclined to the opinion which doth affirm</hi> the Inſtitution of Bishops, &amp; the Obligation of Reſidence, <hi>to be</hi> de jure divino; <hi>but, though it were certainly true, he ſaw no neceſſity, or opportunity, to proceed to a declaration thereof.</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, when <hi>Lorain</hi> came to Council,
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 596.</note> 
               <hi>The Bishop of</hi> Liria, <hi>to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form</hi> him <hi>of all the reaſons of the</hi> Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards, <hi>did recapitulate, with great elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, whatſoever they had ſaid in this
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:33183:49"/>matter: And added beſides, that nothing was more in favour of the Lutherans, than to ſay that Bishops are inſtituted by the Law of man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When <hi>Lorain</hi> gave his ſuffrage, he propoſed the reaſons on both ſides; he
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 596.</note> 
               <hi>concluded in the end, that the Queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was boundleſs;</hi> and <hi>exhorted the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to leave it, omitting</hi> jure divino, <hi>&amp; ſaying</hi> inſtituted by <hi>Chriſt.</hi> But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this,
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The</hi> French <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, who ſpoke after</hi> Lorain, <hi>did not uſe the ſame ambiguity, but maintain'd openly, that the Authority of Bishops was</hi> de jure divino.</p>
            <p>Again, in another Congregation,
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 598.</note> 
               <hi>The</hi> French <hi>made proof of their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. They ſaid, that the Inſtitution &amp; Juriſdiction of Bishops was</hi> de jure di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vino, <hi>as well as that of the Pope; that there was no difference, but in degree of Superiority; and that the Pope's Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is confined within the limits of the Canons, relating &amp; commending the ſtile of the Parliaments of</hi> France, <hi>that when any Pope's Bull is preſented, which containeth any thing contrary to the Canons receiv'd in</hi> France, <hi>they pronounce it to be abuſive, &amp; forbid the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</hi>
               <pb n="242" facs="tcp:33183:50"/>Have you never heard, that ſuch boldneſs as this, even in a free Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, has been enough to ſend a man to the Tower? And yet, <hi>Soave</hi> confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>They were heard with much pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.</hi> Conſider well theſe paſſages, from the beginning to the end of this Diſpute; and tell me then, what liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was wanting in the Council.</p>
            <p n="27">XXVII. If the Prelates were ſo bold, &amp; took ſuch liberty, How was it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for the Council to end ſo quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? A. In ſome matters, they had full
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 728.</note> 
               <hi>ſatisfaction;</hi> as in the clauſe, <hi>Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentibus Legatis.</hi> In ſome, a <hi>conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part</hi> oppoſed, as in the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Reſidence;</hi> which therefore, according to the
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 538.</note> 
               <hi>general Maxim</hi> of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, could not be determin'd. In others, as the <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of Bishops, &amp; the Pope's <hi>Authority,</hi> although their argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments had been urged, repeated, &amp; am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified, in ſeveral Congregations, yet ſtill the major part was of another opinion; it was, therefore, impoſſible to come to any determination: And, you know, how natural it is, for reaſonable men, to be quiet and ſilent, when they plainly ſee, it is in vain to ſpeak.</p>
            <pb n="243" facs="tcp:33183:50"/>
            <p n="28">XXVIII. Was not the Pope's Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, at length, made uſe of, to reſtrain their liberty, under pretence of their abuſing it? A. <hi>Soave</hi> himſelf, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver makes the beſt of things, is pleas'd to tell us quite another ſtory. <hi>Lorain</hi> (who, at his firſt coming to <hi>Trent,</hi> had oppos'd the
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 583.</note> 
               <hi>declaration</hi> of theſe points, &amp; had
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 596.</note> 
               <hi>exhorted the Fathers to leave it)
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 684.</note> propoſed the omiſſion of the two Articles, of the Inſtitution of Bishops, and Authority of the Pope, as things wherein the parties were too paſſionate.</hi> And <hi>very fitly,</hi> ſays your Author,
<note n="*" place="bottom">ibid.</note> 
               <hi>an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der came from the Emperour to his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, to uſe all means that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Pope should not be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſs'd in Council; which his Majeſty did, becauſe he ſaw the major part inclined to enlarge it ... The Ambaſſadors, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving treated with the Legates in confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity hereof, as alſo with</hi> Lorain, <hi>&amp; other principal Prelates, did cauſe this Article to be omitted, as alſo that other of the Inſtitution of Bishops. But firſt they made many conſultations about it, that all might reſt contented.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="29">XXIX. Why were the Popes, of thoſe times, ſo afraid of a General Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil?
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:33183:51"/>Why ſo averſe from it? Why did they, to ſecure themſelves, shift ſides ſo often betwixt the Emperour &amp; King of <hi>France?</hi> A. You might as well have ask'd me, Why dos a Pilot fear a ſtorm? Why is he ſo averſe from it? Why dos he trimm the boat ſo often? S. <hi>Peter's Ship,</hi> in thoſe days, was grievouſly toſs'd, &amp; almoſt <hi>coverd with the waves:</hi> But our Lord, who ſeem'd to <hi>ſleep,</hi> at length <hi>aroſe,</hi> commanded <hi>the winds &amp; the Sea,</hi> &amp; there follow'd <hi>a great Calm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="30">XXX. Why did they avoid, &amp; defer ſo long, the General Reformation? Why were Bulls given ſecretly to the Legates, to ſuſpend or transfer the Council, as occaſion ſerv'd? Why did they open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare, that a Council is ever dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, when the Pope's Authority is queſtion'd? A. You'l never have done with theſe cramp-queſtions, except a man give you as good as you bring. Is not the <hi>Reformation</hi> of <hi>Abuſes,</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> as dangerous as the <hi>Redreſſing</hi> of <hi>Grievances,</hi> in the <hi>State?</hi> If our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were in the ſame ferment, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the reign of <hi>Charles I.</hi> would you blame his Majeſty for pretending to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogue or diſſolve as he pleaſes? And have we not, ever ſince, great reaſon to
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:33183:51"/>believe that a Parliament (though, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, excellent in it ſelf) is always dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, when the King's Authority is queſtion'd? In thoſe tumults of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Affairs, <hi>Reformation</hi> was a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous buſineſs: And, had the Reformers been <hi>let ſlip</hi> at the <hi>Abuſes,</hi> they would perhaps have <hi>worry'd</hi> the whole <hi>Church.</hi> If <hi>S. Paul</hi> was <hi>in perils among falſe Brethren,</hi> the Succeſſor of <hi>S. Peter</hi> was no leſs.
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 284.</note> 
               <hi>Not only the Proteſtants did impugn</hi> his <hi>Authority, but many Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces alſo would reſtrain it, &amp; many Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops did think to moderate it.
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 205.</note> The Spaniards had a ſecret, which they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated only among themſelves, to make great the Epiſcopal Authority, ſo that the Pope could not reſtrain it.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> had
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 522.</note> 
               <hi>ever pretended to limit the Pope's power, &amp; ſubject it to the Canons &amp; Councils,
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 34<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> The Emperour's Ambaſſadors had given the Proteſtants hope to moderate the Papal Authority, &amp; ſaid that they expected to ſee a Gate laid open by their negotiation, that after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards they might ſecond it:</hi> and <hi>Julius</hi> III. <hi>had intelligence, that the Emperour had a deſign to advance himſelf, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſing of the Papacy.</hi> This was enough
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:33183:52"/>to make the Popes, of that Age, take care to look before they leap'd. But yet this was not all, if <hi>Soave</hi> ſays true. The
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Governours of Countries regarded not much, what the Council might deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine concerning Doctrines; but deſired it might be ſuch a one, as might reduce the Prieſts &amp; Friers to their beginning; hoping that by that means the regalities &amp; temporal jurisdictions might return unto them. And therefore they ſaid, it was in vain to call a Council where the Bishops, &amp; other Prelates, only, should have a deliberative voice; becauſe they ought to be reform'd, and it was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that others should have the charge thereof, who could not be deceiv'd by their proper intereſts.</hi> Here you ſee, in plain English, what the <hi>Reformation</hi> was like to come to. 1. The deſign was laid to bring the Eccleſiaſticks <hi>to their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning:</hi> They were to be brought to their <hi>Staff</hi> and <hi>Scrip</hi> again, &amp; ſent about their buſineſs, whilſt the Reformers plunder'd the Church, &amp; divided the ſpoiles. 2. To do it with more eaſe, <hi>it was in vain to call a Council of Bishops,</hi> but the Laity were to <hi>have the charge thereof, who could not be deceiv'd by their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per intereſts.</hi> This Reaſon, I confeſs, if
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:33183:52"/>it had taken place, would have been worth it's weight in gold: but, pray, give me leave to make the caſe your own. Suppoſe a man should demand your purſe; and, upon refuſal, tell you He is the better Judge, whether or no you ought to deliver; becauſe your intereſt blinds you but He <hi>cannot be deceiv'd by his proper intereſt.</hi> Would you believe this honeſt Gentleman? How did you like this method of <hi>Reforming,</hi> when our English Rebels threw the <hi>Sovereign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> out of doors, &amp; the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> out of the windows? Did you fancy that thoſe <hi>Church-and-State-Menders</hi> deſerv'd <hi>to have the charge of</hi> thoſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and that <hi>it was neceſſary</hi> they <hi>should have</hi> it, becauſe they <hi>could not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd by their proper intereſts?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If ſuch a Throughout-Reformation as this, had been effectually procured, All had been well: Complaints would then have ceas'd, becauſe there would have been nothing left to complain of: The Reformers would have <hi>reduced</hi> the Pope, the Cardinals, the Bishops Prieſts &amp; Friers, <hi>to their beginning,</hi> which in plain English is little better than <hi>reducing</hi> them <hi>to their end:</hi> The Faction would then have triumph'd, according to their hearts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire;
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:33183:53"/>juſt as our Rebels did, when they had brought our Monarchy to it's <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning,</hi> by beheading of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But, this not being effected, All the reſt was nothing to the purpoſe. One would think that eleven or twelve De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, containing above 140. chapters of Reformation, might be ſome degree of ſatisfaction to any reaſonable men: But, when people are diſappointed in their principal deſign, right or wrong 'tis all the ſame, they are out of humour; and, when they are ſo, tis a hard matter to pleaſe them. This was the reaſon why the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Criticks were ſo sharp in cenſuring &amp; ridiculing the Decrees, as ſoon as each Seſſion of the Council was publish'd in <hi>Germany.</hi> p. 504. <hi>The Birth of the Mountains,</hi> was a proverb much in vogue, which <hi>Soave</hi> has recorded in more places than one, though otherwiſe worded, <hi>The travail of the mountains, and the nativity of the mouſe:</hi> an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion proper enough to let us under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, what vaſt projects they had laid of <hi>reducing</hi> all things <hi>to their beginning;</hi> &amp; how much they were diſappointed in them; ſince what was decreed by the Council, compar'd with what they would have done themſelves, was no
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:33183:53"/>more than a <hi>mouſe</hi> to a <hi>mountain.</hi> In the ſame page, he goes on; <hi>Concerning the Reformation it was ſaid, that more light points could not be handled, nor more lightly; and that they did imitate the Phyſician, who, in a hectical body, laboured to kill the Itch.</hi> This was ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pleaſant jeſt, which <hi>Soave</hi> took care of, for fear it should be loſt. But, let him jeſt as he pleaſes, the <hi>Itch,</hi> he talks of, is not ſo eaſily cured. This humour, of Reforming, is a very <hi>itching</hi> humour: And the <hi>Itch</hi> is a ſtrange reſtleſs diſeaſe: Even the wiſer ſort of mankind, when they have once got it, cannot for their lives forbear <hi>Scratching,</hi> though they know by experience that it dos more harm than good.</p>
            <p>Read the Decrees of Reformation from the beginning to the end, and if you read them with a ſerious attention, I am very confident, an impartial man, as you are, will not ſay they are, either <hi>light,</hi> or <hi>lightly handled.</hi> If you have the <hi>Council</hi> in your Library, I had rather you would read them there, than in <hi>Soave;</hi> who, I muſt needs tell you, is not ſo exact as I could wish him. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of relating the <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> he leaves out a great many circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:33183:54"/>which a curious man would be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to know: And beſides, although I have compar'd a very ſmall part of his tranſlation with the original, I find ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral miſtakes in it. p. 503. n. 1. he reads <hi>is,</hi> for <hi>is not.</hi> p. 692. n. 12. he reads <hi>ſix,</hi> for <hi>five.</hi> p. 733. n. 2. he reads <hi>two,</hi> for <hi>three.</hi> p 753. n. 1. of two expreſs <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,</hi> he has made only one <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation.</hi> Such negligences as theſe are enough to make me ſuſpect him in other matters; &amp; are a great argument that it was more his buſineſs, to find fault with the Reformation, than to give an exact account of it. But, whether you conſult the <hi>Council</hi> or his <hi>Hiſtory,</hi> that you may find out all the Decrees in order, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any trouble, I have directed you to all the <hi>Seſſions</hi> of the one, &amp; <hi>pages</hi> of the other. V. 173.174. VI. 211.212. VII. 247.248. XIII. 320.321. XIV 331.332.333.334. XXI. 503. XXII. 537.538. XXIII 691.692.693. XXIV. 730.731.732.733.734.735. XXV. 751.752.753.754.755.756. And, for your better ſatisfaction, I have ſet down ſome few inſtances of <hi>Soave</hi>'s Tranſlation, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring it with the Original, &amp; enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, what he has either alter'd or omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in a parentheſis like [this.]</p>
            <pb n="251" facs="tcp:33183:54"/>
            <p n="1">1. Concerning Scripture. The firſt point of Reformation, in the firſt chapter, of the firſt Decree, is this,
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 173. n. 1.</note> 
               <hi>that in the Churches, where there is a ſtipend allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for reading Divinity, the Bishop should provide that the Holy Scripture should be read by the Stipendary, if he be fit; and, not being fit, the Bishop should depute a Subſtitute to perform the charge: But, for hereafter, that the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice should not be conferred but upon a ſufficient perſon. That in the Cathedral Churches of populous Cities, &amp; Collegiate Churches of great Caſtles, where no ſuch ſtipend is aſſign'd, the firſt Prebend that falleth void, should be applied to that uſe, or a ſimple Benefice, or a contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all Beneficed men, to inſtitute the Lecture.</hi> And again, concerning
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 693. n. 18.</note> 
               <hi>the inſtitution of Seminaries, it was conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that every Epiſcopal Church should have a certain number of boys, brought up in a Colledge, to learn,</hi> among other things, <hi>the Holy Scripture.</hi> All this
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 5. c. 1.</note> 
               <hi>The Holy Synod ordereth &amp; decreeth [leaſt that heavenly Treaſure of Sacred Books, which the Holy Ghoſt has ſo libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally beſtow'd upon mankind, should lye neglected.]</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="252" facs="tcp:33183:55"/>
            <p n="2">2. Concerning Eccleſiaſticks.
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 732. n. 1.</note> 
               <hi>The Decrees of Reformation did contain, That whoſoever have right in the Promotion, shall be admonished that it is a mortal ſin, if they shall not uſe all diligence to promote the moſt worthy &amp; moſt profitable to the Church. And it was added, How neceſſary it is, that the Pope, in regard of his Duty, should endeavour to aſſume Cardinals of [moſt] excellent worth, &amp; to provide the Church of fit Paſtors, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if the flock should perish by [the evil government of perſons negligent &amp; forgetfull of their duty]</hi> Chriſt <hi>will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand an account of his Holineſs.
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 733. n. 3.</note> That [Patriarchs, Primates, Metropolitans, &amp;] Bishops, shall be bound to viſit [their proper] Dioceſs... That the Viſitor shall go with a modeſt train of men &amp; horſes, diſpatching the Viſitation, as ſoon as may be; and shall not receive any [money, or preſent, whatſoever it be, or in what manner ſoever it be offered] but frugal &amp; moderate Diet ...
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                     <hi>ibid.</hi> n. 4.</note> That the Bishops shall be bound to preach in perſon; or, having a lawfull impediment, by others. And in caſe the Parish Prieſt be hindred, that he cannot preach in his own Church, he shall, at his charge, maintain another
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:33183:55"/>to do it, deputed by the Bishops... That the Bishop shall admonish every one [that, where it may conveniently be done, he ought] to go to his own Parish, to hear the Sermon: and that None [either Secular, or Regular, even in the Churches of their own Order,] shall preach againſt the Bishop's will.
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 734, n. 10.</note> That where Viſitation, or Correction of manners, is in queſtion, no exemption or appeal, though to the Apoſtolick See, shall [any way] hinder or ſuſpend the execution of that which is decreed or adjudged.
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 735. n, 17.</note> That no Eccleſiaſtical perſon, though a Cardinal, shall have more than one Benefice, which not being able to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him, another ſimple Benefice may be added, ſo that they do not both require Reſidence; which shall be underſtood of all Benefices, of what title or quality ſoever, though Commended. And he that hath now more Benefices than one, shall be bound to leave all but one, within ſix months; or, if not, they shall be all void.
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 753. n, 1.</note> The Reading of the General Reformation did follow, which, after an Exhortation to Bishops, for exemplary life, [commandeth, not only that they be content with] modeſty &amp; frugality
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:33183:56"/>of [houshold-ſtuff &amp; table; but alſo, that in the reſt of their way of living, &amp; in their whole houſe, nothing may appear but what bears the character of ſimplicity, zeal, &amp; contempt of Vanities: And abſolutely] doth forbid them to enrich their friends or kindred, with the revenues of the Church; but, if poor, to allot them their diſtribution, as to the reſt of the poor. What has been ſaid of Bishops, it Decreeth to be obſerved by all beneficed Eccleaſticks, either Secular or Regular, and alſo by the Cardinals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here I have cited only eight points, a very inconſiderable part, of the whole <hi>Reformation</hi> which contains above a hundred &amp; forty chapters: But, for a man of your skill, a <hi>pattern</hi> is enough to judge of the <hi>whole piece.</hi> And, beſides all theſe Decrees, there are alſo others of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> forbidding &amp; condemning ſeveral abuſes, which are worth your taking notice of.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Concerning Purgatory
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 75<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>The Synod teaches</hi> no more, than <hi>that there is a Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, &amp; that the Souls detain'd in it, are aſſiſted by the ſuffrages of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, &amp; the Sacrifice of the Maſs. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it doth command Bishops to teach ſound doctrine in this matter [ſuch as is
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:33183:56"/>deliver'd by the Holy Fathers, &amp; Sacred Councils] and cauſe it to be preached, without handling ſubtil queſtions before the ignorant people, nor ſuffering uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain &amp; unlikely things to be published; Prohibiting curioſities, ſuperſtition, &amp; unhoneſt gain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Concerning Maſſes.
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 537.</note> 
               <hi>A Decree was read concerning abuſes, to be correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in the celebration of Maſſes: And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in ſubſtance; that the Bishops ought to forbid all things brought in by Avarice, Irreverence, or Superſtition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3.<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 751.</note> 
               <hi>In matter of Saints, it doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand Bishops, &amp; all others who have the charge of teaching, to inſtruct the people concerning the interceſſion &amp; invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of them, according to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient doctrine of the Church, conſent of Fathers, &amp; decrees of Councils, teaching, that the Saints do pray for men, that it is profitable to invocate them, &amp; to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to their prayers &amp; aſſiſtance, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain benefits from God, through</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>his Son our Lord, who is our onely Saviour &amp; Redeemer. Concerning Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges;</hi> that <hi>thoſe of</hi> Chriſt <hi>&amp; the Saints, ought to have due honour given them;</hi> but <hi>that there is no divinity or virtue in
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:33183:57"/>them ... Afterwards it addeth, that, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to take away the abuſes, &amp; occaſions of pernicious errors, it doth Ordain ... that all Superſtition, in invocation of Saints, in worship of Reliques, &amp; in uſe of Images, be taken away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Concerning Indulgences.
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 757.</note> 
               <hi>The Synod doth</hi> only <hi>anathematize thoſe that shall ſay, they are unprofitable, &amp; that the Church hath not power to grant them. It doth command that all thoſe offices of Pardon-mongers be abolished: And, for the other abuſes [which have taken their riſe from ſuperſtition, ignorance, irreverence, or any other way, Whereas they cannot conveniently be forbidden, in particular, by reaſon of the manifold cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of provinces, &amp; places where they are committed,] it doth command the Bishops, that every one shall collect all</hi> thoſe <hi>of his own Church, to propoſe them in the Provincial Synod,
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 733, n. 2.</note> which shall be call'd by the Metropolitan, or the moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Suffragan, within one year, at the moſt, after the end of this Synod, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, every [three] years, at leaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tell me now your opinion concerning theſe matters, All theſe <hi>points,</hi> are they <hi>light,</hi> and <hi>lightly handled?</hi> Are they all
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:33183:57"/>nothing to the purpoſe? Suppoſe the <hi>Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard</hi> had been a little neglected, &amp; the <hi>Vines</hi> wanted <hi>pruning,</hi> Will nothing elſe ſerve your turn, but <hi>reducing</hi> them <hi>to their beginning,</hi> &amp; cutting them up by the Roots?</p>
            <p>I had almoſt quite forgot to tell you that, in the end of the <hi>General Reformation,</hi> the Council has taken particular care, that no Diſpenſing power may obſtruct the force &amp; benefit of the Decrees. <hi>Be it known to all men,</hi> ſays the Council,
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 756. n. 18.</note> 
               <hi>that the Canons shall be obſerved [exactly &amp;] in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinctly by all, &amp; shall not be diſpenſed, but for [an urgent and juſt] cauſe, heard with [great] maturity, &amp; without coſt [by whoſoere they are, to whom it appertains: Otherwiſe, the Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion shall be judg'd Surreptitious.]</hi> If the <hi>Cauſe</hi> be, not only <hi>juſt</hi> but <hi>urgent;</hi> if the <hi>juſtice</hi> and <hi>urgency</hi> be well <hi>known</hi> before the grant of it; if nothing be given to any <hi>whoſoever</hi> for it; Such a Diſpenſation is unqueſtionably blameleſs. And now, I deſire to know, How was it poſſible for the Council to provide more effectually for the punctual obſervance of all theſe three conditions, than by declaring that <hi>otherwiſe</hi> the <hi>Diſpenſation</hi> is, &amp; shall be, <hi>ſurreptitious,</hi> &amp; of no effect?</p>
            <p n="31">XXXI. In the end of the Council, there
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:33183:58"/>was great joy in Rome, for having chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the world, and advanced their inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, where they fear'd to have their wings clipp'd. A. Here I know not how you'l be able to make the two ends of <hi>Soave's</hi> Hiſtory meet. In his firſt book, he talks much at this rate; and, in his laſt, he largely contradicts it. He tells us, in the end, how the Pope and Cardinals delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated upon the matter, whether or no the Decrees of Reformation, were to be confirmed; And ſays, that
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 759.</note> 
               <hi>the Court, underſtanding that the Pope was reſolved upon the Confirmation, chang'd their joy into grief; All the Officers complain'd of the loſſes they should receive in their offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, if that Reformation were executed... Supplications alſo, &amp; Memorials, were given to the Pope, by thoſe, who, having bought their Offices, &amp; foreſeeing this loſs, demanded reſtitution... The Pope having diligently conſider'd thereof, deputed eight Cardinals to conſult upon the Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; &amp; to think upon ſome remedies for the complaints of the Court...</hi> He concludes, <hi>It is certain, that they who did procure the Council, had no aim but to pull down the Pope's Authority; And, while the Council did laſt, every one did ſpeak, as if it had power to give Laws to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After all, you think to mortifie me
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:33183:58"/>with objecting, that the corruptions of the <hi>Court,</hi> &amp; the abuſes tolerated in the <hi>Church,</hi> are as great as ever. But you muſt give me leave to tell you, 1. I am not obliged to take your bare word for't; 2. Whether it be true or falſe, 'tis nothing to my preſent purpoſe. If falſe, you are to blame for ſaying ſo: If true, 'tis none of the Council's fault. Having proceeded legal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; having made good Laws, the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil has done its part: 'tis ours, to do the reſt. My buſineſs is to defend the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil: I have nothing to do, to rake the dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill of the Church. Has the <hi>Decalogue</hi> leſs Authority, becauſe the greateſt part of mankind are ſo diſobedient? Or is the <hi>Ghoſpel</hi> leſs Sacred, becauſe there are ſo few who live according to the maxims of it? If this be the onely reaſon, why you Proteſt againſt the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Decrees of Reformation are not every where, in all things, punctually obſerv'd; I ſee no reaſon, why you may not, with as good a grace, Proteſt againſt the <hi>Ghoſpel,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Ten Commandments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have now done with your Objections: And although I am not of the Poet's mind, that <hi>Brevity is always good, be it, or be it not, underſtood;</hi> Yet I have endeavour'd to be as short as poſſibly I could, becauſe, when I deal with a man of your parts, a
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:33183:59"/>word is enough to the wiſe, &amp; few words are beſt.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Soave,</hi> whom you ſo much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, I deſire to ask you a few queſtions, before I tell you what I think of him. Suppoſe a mortal enemy of yours should <hi>Libel</hi> you, by the way of <hi>Hiſtory;</hi> call you <hi>Rogue</hi> &amp; <hi>Raſcal</hi> in the very Preface; and, at the ſame time, perſwade his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that he <hi>follows exactly the truth:</hi> Would you have me take this Author for an Oracle? Would you not think me rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, if I ſuſpected almoſt every word he ſaid? And ought not I to do the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil</hi> as much Juſtice, as I would my <hi>Friend?</hi> Tis certain that <hi>Soave</hi> was a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal enemy of the Council: In the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, he declares it: He ſays,
<note n="*" place="bottom">p. 2.</note> 
               <hi>it has cauſed the greateſt deformation that ever was,</hi> &amp; calls it <hi>the Iliad of the Age;</hi> which is as kind a compliment to the Fathers, as if he had call'd them, a pack of <hi>Villains.</hi> He tells us indeed, in the ſame place, that he is <hi>not poſſeſs'd with any paſſion, which may make him erre;</hi> and this was well enough ſaid; But how shall a body do to believe him? If it were your own caſe, I'm ſure you would not like my being credulous: And how do I know but that an Enemy of the Council
<pb n="261" facs="tcp:33183:59"/>may deſerve as little credit, as an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of yours?</p>
            <p>Another reaſon, why I do not like him, is becauſe he takes upon him to write men's private thoughts, with as much aſſurance as he writes their words and actions. He hardly ever ſpeaks of any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence coming to <hi>Rome,</hi> but he enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains his Reader with a pleaſant Scene, in which he brings the Pope alone upon the Stage, diſcourſing with himſelf his ſecret apprehenſions &amp; deliberations upon every matter; ſuch thoughts as no wiſe man would truſt his neighbour with, although he were the beſt &amp; ſureſt friend he had in the world. How <hi>Soave</hi> could poſſibly come to any certain knowledg of ſuch things, I am not able to comprehend: And truly, if a man, in one caſe, will tell me more than he <hi>can</hi> know; I have juſt reaſon to be afraid that, in another, he'l tell me more than he <hi>dos</hi> know.</p>
            <p>A third reaſon, which weighs more with me than all the reſt, is this: You tell me, on the one ſide, He was a <hi>Popish Frier;</hi> And, on the other, I cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, but that (although perhaps, for ſome reaſons, he did not openly profeſs it) He was really a <hi>Proteſtant.</hi> It appears ſo plainly, by his cenſuring the Decrees of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> as well as thoſe of <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
               <pb n="262" facs="tcp:33183:60"/>&amp; by the ſevere reflections of his own, which he intermixes with thoſe of the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Criticks; that I do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive how any man of ſenſe, who reads him with attention, can be of another opinion. Had he been a barefaced Proteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, I should be more inclined to believe him. There is ſomething of integrity &amp; honour in a man that openly profeſſes what he is: And, although paſſion &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice may blind him, yet I am apt to think that ſuch a perſon will never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive me, more than he deceives himſelf. But a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> that lives &amp; dies in the profeſſion of a <hi>Popish Frier,</hi> How can I believe his <hi>words,</hi> when the moſt ſerious of his <hi>actions</hi> are only ſo many lies ? For my own part, I would as ſoon make choice of a <hi>Catholick Jew</hi> to comment upon the Ghoſpel, &amp; to write the life of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as I would chooſe a <hi>Proteſtant Frier</hi> to write the Hiſtory of a <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Council.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I end my Letter, give me leave, once more, to mind you of the Diſcourſe we had, when we ſaw one another laſt. We both agreed, that
<note n="*" place="bottom">C. II. p. 1.</note> 
               <hi>it were a very irrational thing to make Laws for a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, &amp; leave it to the inhabitants to be the Interpreters &amp; Judges of thoſe Laws; for then every man will be his own Judge,
<pb n="263" facs="tcp:33183:60"/>&amp; by conſequence no ſuch thing as either Right or Wrong:</hi> that
<note n="*" place="bottom">ibid.</note> 
               <hi>therefore we cannot ſuppoſe, that God Almighty would leave us at thoſe Uncertainties, as to give us a Rule to go by, &amp; leave every man to be his own Judge:</hi> that
<note n="*" place="bottom">ib.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt left his Spirit &amp; Power to his Church, by which they were the Judges, even of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelf, many years after the Apoſtles-which Books were Canonical, &amp; which were not:</hi> that
<note n="*" place="bottom">
                  <hi>ibid.</hi> p. 2.</note> 
               <hi>the Judgment of the Church, is without Appeal; otherwiſe, what they decide would be no farther to be follow'd than it agrees with every man's private Judgment:</hi> that <hi>becauſe, in the Apoſtles Creed, we believe in the Holy Catholick Church, therefore we ought to believe in the firſt four General Councils, which were true &amp; legal Repreſentatives of it:</hi> And laſtly, that <hi>if the Council of</hi> Trent <hi>were prov'd to be as General, as free, &amp; as legal in all it's circumſtances, as any of the firſt four Councils were; then you muſt needs own your ſelf obliged in Conſcience to ſubmit to it, &amp; to leave of Proteſting againſt it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This laſt part I have here endeavour'd to prove, out of <hi>Soave</hi> himſelf, your own Hiſtorian, who always makes the worſt of things, &amp; never ſpeaks a favourable
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:33183:61"/>word, but when the Power of Truth conſtrains him to it. If I have not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd according to expectation; 'tis your own fault, who are to blame for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a better opinion of me than I deſerve. I am no Doctor, nor Graduate; but every way unfit to be a Champion of the Cauſe. Yet, having receiv'd your Commands, I have juſt reaſon to expect, that you will eaſily pardon a man, who in this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is guilty of no other crime than being ready to shew himſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Sept. 22. 1686.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Obedient Servant, N. N.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>
               <hi>Page.</hi> 70. <hi>line.</hi> 1. <hi>read.</hi> rewarded. p. 75. *. 4. r. <hi>ch.</hi> 14. p. 76. l. 8. r. his 9. book. p. 85. l. 26. r. many. p. 86. l. 29. r. the year 831. p. 89. l. 8. dele <hi>de.</hi> p. 114. l. 21. r. his 2. book. p. 152. l. 27. r. shut out. p. 161. l. 6. r. it has. p. 165. l. 1. r. your. p. 168. l. 5. r. <hi>haereticis.</hi> p. 172. l. 3. dele an. p. 176. l. 26. r. in this. p. 189. l. 22. r. <hi>to</hi> Baſil. p. 190. l. 9. r. the caſe. ibid. l. 13. r. <hi>HAERETICIS.</hi> p. 194. l. 1. r. another. p. 225 l. 3. r. <hi>Charles</hi> II. p. 240. *. 2. r. 590.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:33183:61"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
